<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two treatises of the Lord his holie Supper the one instructing the seruants of God how they should be prepared when they come to the holy Supper of our onely Sauiour Iesus Christ: whereunto is annexed a dialogue conteining the principall points necessarie to be knowne and vnderstood of all them that are to be partakers of the holy Supper: the other setting forth dialoguewise the whole vse of the Supper: whereunto also is adioyned a briefe and learned treatise of the true Sacrifice and true priest. Written in the French tongue by Yues Rouspeau and Iohn de l'Espine ministers of the word of God, and latelie translated into English.</title>
            <author>Rouspeau, Yves.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1584</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 205 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11086</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21354</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106120</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841845</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841845</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6460</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11086)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6460)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 581:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two treatises of the Lord his holie Supper the one instructing the seruants of God how they should be prepared when they come to the holy Supper of our onely Sauiour Iesus Christ: whereunto is annexed a dialogue conteining the principall points necessarie to be knowne and vnderstood of all them that are to be partakers of the holy Supper: the other setting forth dialoguewise the whole vse of the Supper: whereunto also is adioyned a briefe and learned treatise of the true Sacrifice and true priest. Written in the French tongue by Yues Rouspeau and Iohn de l'Espine ministers of the word of God, and latelie translated into English.</title>
                  <author>Rouspeau, Yves.</author>
                  <author>L'Espine, Jean de, ca. 1506-1597. Dialogue de la Cène de N.S. Jesus-Christ. aut</author>
                  <author>Rouspeau, Yves. Traitté de la préparation à la saincte cene.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>58 [i.e. 56], 70 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Thomas Thomas printer to the Vniuersitie of Cambridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1584.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In two parts. The first treatise is a translation of: Rouspeau, Yves. Traitté de la préparation à la saincte cene de nostre seul sauveur .. Plus un dialogue contant les poincts principaux que ceux qui veulent recevoir la cene doivent savoir et entendre. The second is a translation of: L'Espine, Jean de. Dialogue de la Cène de N.S. Jesus-Christ. Plus un traitté du vray sacrifice..</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in pagination of first sequence; correct pagination deduced from signature collation.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C D⁴ [2d]B-E F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6460:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6460:1"/>
            <p>TWO TREATISES OF THE LORD HIS HOLIE SVPPER: THE ONE INSTRVCTING THE SERVANTS OF GOD HOW THEY ſhould be prepared when they come to the holy Supper of our onely Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereunto is annexed a Dialogue conteining the principall points neceſſarie to be knowne and vnderstood of all them that are to be partakers of the holy Supper:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other ſetting forth Dialoguewiſe the whole vſe of the Supper: Whereunto alſo is adioyned a briefe and learned treatiſe of the true Sacrifice and true Prieſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written in the French tongue by Yues Rouſpeau and Iohn de l'Eſpine Ministers of the word of God, and latelie tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>1. CORINTH. 11.28.</bibl> Let a man examine himſelfe, and ſo let him eate of this bread, and drinke of this cup.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>IOHN 6.58.</bibl> This is the bread which came downe from heauen: not as your fathers haue eaten Manna, and are dead. He that eateth of this bread, ſhall liue for euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>PSAL. 51.16.</bibl> Thou deſireſt no ſacrifice, though we would giue it: thou deliteſt not in burnt offering. The ſacrifices of God are a contrite ſpirit: a contrite and broken heart, O God, thou wilt not deſpiſe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted by Thomas Thomas Printer to the Vniuerſitie of Cambridge. 1584.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6460:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6460:2"/>
            <head>YVES ROVSPEAV TO THE CHRISTIAN READER, FROM OVR LORD IESVS CHRIST greeting.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong the cauſes of all publique ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, and of the ſcourges where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall diuerſe realmes &amp; countries are grieuouſly chaſtiſed: S. Paul ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth mention of the notable abuſe &amp; contempt of the Lord his Supper. <hi>For this cauſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>manie are weake &amp; ſicke among you, &amp; many ſleepe: for if we would iudge our ſelues, we ſhould not be iudged.</hi> Wherupon we haue not to meruaile, that the Lord God hath ſo ſharply puniſhed this poore realme of France the laſt yeare, <hi>1562.</hi> with plague, warre, and famine, ſeeing it is manifest that the contempt of the Goſpel with the abuſing and profaning of the holie Supper of the Lord, hath brought vpon vs the foreſaid miſeries &amp; afflictions. And for this cauſe, both the Pope his adherents may ſtop their mouthes, with the which they are ſo readie to cast reproch vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our God, and they that make profeſſion of the Goſpel in this lan<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may keepe like ſilence, ſeeing the cauſes haue flowed from both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties indifferently, and the fault belongeth as wel to the one, as to the other. To begin with the Papists, we may boldly auouch out of the word of God, that their Maſſe is ſtuffed full of blaſphemies: that it aboliſheth the holy Supper of our Lord Ieſus Christ: that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of his death &amp; paſſion is therein ſuppreſsed &amp; made o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> none effect: that in the ſame there is no communion: &amp; that, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Ieſus Christ hath giuen a generall charge to all the profeſſors o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:6460:3"/>
his name, to take, eate, and drinke the bread and wine, in the Maſse there is but one that taketh, eateth &amp; drinketh for all the reſt. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we ſee how there the creature of God, euen a morſell of breade, is worſhiped in the place of God himſelfe the creator: how they ſeeke Christ Ieſus vpon the earth, whereas the word of God, the Creed of the Apoſtles, and the ancient Canons do teach vs to haue our hearts lifted vp on high, and to ſeeke him by Faith aboue in the heauens. Laſtlie, in it we may behold manie other most ſhamefull and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous abuſes, which for this time I thinke beſt to couer with ſilence. Now ſeing that manie do ſo ſtoutly and obſtinately ſtand vpon that point, that in the defence and quarrell of a thing ſo vile &amp; wicked, they haue put to death ſo manie godlie and honest men, ſo many ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie perſonages and true martyrs of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, I conclude that we haue iustly beene viſited of God for their offences. As for the Protestants, we ſee they alſo haue beene marked with the foule ſpots and blemiſhes of manie groſſe and notable abuſes. How many of them haue bin found as vnable to render reaſon of their Faith as verie Papiſts, &amp; haue offered, like bruit beaſts, their preſence at the holy Supper of the Lord, ſome for learning as ignorant as Aſſes, others for life, as beastly as ſwyne. I ouerpaſse an infinite number of hypocrites, of falſe brethren, of traitours, and ſuch as haue fallen from their faith and knowledge, who being inwardly vnknowen, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried outwardly a ſhew &amp; colour of great vertue and holynes. And therfore not without cauſe hath the wrath of God beene kindled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his people, and they haue receaued double correction, ſeeing that in the ſtrength of their knowledge they haue wittingly abuſed the knowledge of his holy name. Now to the intent that our good God by his Sonne Ieſus Christ may cast his eye of pitie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion vpon this poore realme that lieth ſo deſolate and forlorne: it behooueth the one &amp; the other henceforth to learne, how they may better performe their dutie of ſeruice and honor to their God accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his word, then they haue done in time paſsed: and chieflie that they be verie circumſpect and heedfull not to defile or profane the holie Supper of our Lord in any kind of condition whatſoeuer. To this end I haue addreſsed this ſmall Treatiſe vnto their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, wherin they ſhall find that the true preparing vnto the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, conſisteth not in the furniture of the bodie, in rich and costlie attire, in gorgious and ſtatelie ſhewes, in counterfait colours, and in outward profeſſing of the name of God: but in pureneſſe of heart and vprightneſse of conſcience, that God which is a Spirit, may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be worſhiped of his in Spirit and truth.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:6460:3"/>
            <head>A TREATISE TEA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHING THE SERVANTS OF GOD, HOW THEY SHOVLD BE prepared when they come to the holy <hi>Supper of our onely Redeemer</hi> Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <div type="preface">
               <head>The Preface.</head>
               <p>THat we may worthily come to the holy Supper of our Lord Ieſus Christ, we must examine our ſelues,<note place="margin">The exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our ſelues, and wherein it conſiſteth.</note> as we are adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and counſelled by the Apostle. There be fower principall pointes wherein we haue to ſound our hearts and conſciences at the bottome, namely Faith, Repentance, Thankeſgiuing, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of our God, and Charitie toward our neighbours.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>
                  <hi>OF FAITH.</hi> The first Article.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt it is requiſit that we haue Faith, that is to ſay,<note place="margin">What Faith is.</note> a certaine and vndeceiueable aſſurance, &amp; ſtedfaſt perſwaſion, that God, in the name of his Sonne our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, whom he deliuered vp to death for our behoofe, is a Father to vs of all mercie, fauour, and compaſſion.<note place="margin">The cauſes of Faith God.</note> This Faith commeth not from our ſelues, neither is it built vpon vs, or vpon any thing to be found in vs, but it commeth from God, and is built vpon God
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6460:4"/>
the Father,<note place="margin">His word.</note> the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt, and vpon the promiſes made in the Goſpel,<note place="margin">The holie Ghoſt.</note> which are inwardly ratified in vs by the working of the holy Ghoſt which crieth in our hearts Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba, that is to ſay, Father. And this Faith is nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, confirmed, and increaſed in our hearts by the holy Sacraments.<note place="margin">The Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> For in the Supper, God, moſt like a louing and carefull Father, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he hath brought vs into his Church by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,<note place="margin">The effects of God in the Supper.</note> doth feede vs in ſpririte with the very ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, applying and making proper to euerie one of vs in particular the merite of his death and paſſion.<note place="margin">Why Ieſus Chriſt giueth the bread &amp; the wine of the Supper: and biddeth vs to take eate and drinke. <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.</note> To which purpoſe it is, that Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe doth giue vs the breade and the wine: that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth vs <hi>To eate and to drinke:</hi> that he ſaith, <hi>the bread is his bodie which is giuen for vs, and the wine his blood which is ſhedde for the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our ſinnes.</hi> In which words he giueth himſelfe vnto vs whollie, he wil be our ſpiritual foode and life: he will remaine in vs by his holy Spirite, &amp; will haue vs to abide in him by Faith, to the end that in beleeuing we do not periſh, but may obtaine that life euerlaſting whereof he is the onely inheritor and giuer.<note place="margin">What we learne by the breaking of the bread.</note> In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the breaking of the bread in the Supper ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth for the confirmation of our Faith, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying of our ſaluation: foraſmuch as it aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vs, and cauſeth vs to ſee with our ſpirituall eyes, that Ieſus Chriſt was once in the citie of Hieruſalem broken with the ſorrowes of death,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6460:4"/>
for our deliuerance from euerlaſting death and to purchaſe vnto vs euerlaſting life. And wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as by the commandement of Ieſus Chriſt we take the bread into our hands, &amp; then the cup: and further that we eate the bread and drinke the wine which are conuerted into the food of our bodies: we are taught by the hands of Faith we ſhould ſeiſe vpon our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and embrace him for our onely Sauiour and Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and that by the ſame Faith we ſhould ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituallie eate his bodie, and drinke his blood, continuing in hope of euerlaſting life. But the life of euery man in particular lieth in his owne Faith, according to the confeſſion made in the Apoſtles Creed, wherein it is written for euery one apart to ſaie, <hi>I beleeue,</hi> not in generall, we <hi>beleeue.</hi> We are not in this caſe to buſie or trouble our heads with the faith and beliefe of another, with his worthineſſe or vnworthines, but wholly to reſt and to ſtay vs vpon our own. For S. Paul doth not teach vs that we ſhould examine other men, neither yet that other men ſhould examine vs, but he ſpeaketh plainly and preciſely in theſe words,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Let euerie man examine himſelfe.</hi> Wherefore let euerie one of vs in ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall aſſure his conſcience, <hi>That Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.</note> the true Meſſias, <hi>is come into the world to ſaue ſinners, of whom he ought,</hi> following the example of S. Paul, <hi>to accompt himſelfe the chiefeſt.</hi> Let him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that Ieſus Chriſt came down from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to abide vpon the earth, that he might lift him
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6460:5"/>
vp from the earth into heauen: that Chriſt was made the ſonne of man to make him the childe of God: that he was conceaued by the holie Ghoſt, and was borne of the virgin Marie, to purifie and clenſe the ſinfulneſſe of his concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; birth. Let him perſwade himſelfe that the ſonne of God hath ouercome the deuill, to free him from the crueltie of that tyrant: that he hath fulfilled the whole lawe (louing God his Father with al his hart, power, and ſtrength, &amp; his neighbour as himſelfe) to purchaſe righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes for him: that he made his appearance before Pilate an earthly iudge, &amp; receaued ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of temporall condemnation as an offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to exempt him from appearing before the dreadfull throne of God his iuſtice where he was to heare ſentence of eternall condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pronounced againſt him for his offences committed againſt a God Almightie and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. Let him be aſſured in heart, that the ſame Ieſus Chriſt deſcended into hell for his cauſe, that is to ſay, endured the ſorrowes and terrible pangs of the ſecond death, and the heauie wrath of God, to acquite him from that fearefull iudgement: that he died a death accurſed of God in hanging on the croſſe, to obteine for him both life and bleſſing before God: that he roſe againe from death for an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt pennie and a warrant of his reſurrection: that he aſcended into heauen for a certeine to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of his aſcenſion into the ſame kingdome:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6460:5"/>
that he ſitteth on the right hand of God his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to be for him an euerlaſting Prieſt, Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, King, Defender, Reconciler, and Aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate. And to be ſhort that he ſhall come at his ſecond comming, to his endleſſe conſolation, and perfect redemption. In like manner, it is neceſſarie that euerie one of vs do in particular applie vnto himſelfe all thoſe graces and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures that are in Ieſus Chriſt, in aſmuch as in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing himſelfe vnto vs, he hath alſo giuen vs all his riches. And therefore, in that he is God, it is that we may be partakers of his Diuinitie: in that he is heire and Lord of the whole world, it is that we may haue part of his Lordſhip and inheritance: and that in him we may recouer the title of ſuch poſſeſſions as we loſt in Adam our firſt parent: in that he is the welbeloued of his Father, it is that we alſo may be acceptable in him: in that he is rich, it is to bleſſe vs with his riches: in that he hath all power againſt the Deuill, ſinne, hell, Antichriſt, the world, and all our enimies, it is to be our warrant and defence againſt them al: in that he is righteous &amp; good, it is to iuſtifie vs, &amp; to make vs good: in that he is bleſſed and immortall, it is to indue vs with his bleſſedneſſe and immortalitie. Thus when we ſhall applie vnto our ſelues all the actions and benefites of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larlie, in like manner all his eſſentiall qualities, affying vs wholly in him and in his promiſes, and diſtruſting wholly our owne ſtrength; then
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6460:6"/>
we may boldlie draw neare vnto the table of the Lord, where we ſhall, by the benefite of Faith, haue full fruition of Ieſus Chriſt, God &amp; man, and further ſhall feele the ſame Faith en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and grow in vs exceedingly to our great comfort. And now it behooueth vs to note, that it is impoſſible we ſhould be made one with Ieſus Chriſt and enioy the rich treaſures that are in him, vnleſſe we do firſt renounce An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt &amp; his kingdome: and vnleſſe we haue in vtter abhomination all idolatrie, ſuperſtition, &amp; ſuch traditions of man as are in a direct line ſet againſt the pure ſeruice of God, the bounds and termes whereof are plainely ſet downe in his holy word. Forſeeing that God is our onely creator, &amp; that in the perſon of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt the true Iſaac, in whom al the nations of the earth are bleſſed, he giueth himſelfe entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto vs his creatures; it is great reaſon that in like maner we by Faith ſhould giue and reſigne vp our ſelues whollie to God our maker. And behold, for this cauſe doth God iuſtlie require his people, &amp; command them in his Law, that <hi>They haue no other Gods before him:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>That they loue him with all their heart and ſoule, with all their ſtrength, and vnderstanding:</hi> that is to ſaie, with all their parts, as well inward, as outward. And for this cauſe alſo, God not only reprooueth thoſe that halte on both ſides, but alſo commaundeth that they which ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to ſtrange Goddes, ſhould be put to death.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6460:6"/>
To this purpoſe S. Paul aduertiſing the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians to flie Idolatrie, vſeth an argument ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the coniunction and vnion that we haue with our Lord Ieſus Chriſt in the Supper, ſaying after this manner.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.</note> 
                  <hi>The cuppe of bleſſing which we bleſſe, is it not the communion of the blood of Chriſt? the bread which we breake is it not the communion of the bodie of Chriſt?</hi> As if he would ſaie, that ſeeing the Corinthians did not come to the Supper, ſimplie &amp; onely to receiue thoſe earthlie elements, but really and in deede to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the bodie and blood of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, to the end they might be linked vnto him by Faith, and made fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bone, it ſhould be more then excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding impietie and abhomination to be preſent at the meetings and aſſemblies of infidels, and to take part with them in their idolatries: and therefore the Apoſtle ſoone after addeth to his former reaſon, that the Corinthians <hi>Cannot drinke the cuppe of the Lord and the cuppe of the Deuils: and that they cannot be partakers of the Lord his table and of the table of Deuils.</hi> Wherein he teacheth vs to vnderſtand, that it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, at once to ſerue both God and the Deuill, and that whoſoeuer hath fellowſhip with ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, doth ſet vp a banner of defiance as it were againſt the Lord Ieſus. Foraſmuch as therefore, neither is darkneſſe more contrarie to light, nor vice to vertue, nor death to life, nor hell to heauen, then the Pope and his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6460:7"/>
is contrarie to Chriſt and his holy Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: it is neceſſarie that all thoſe that haue true faith in Ieſus Chriſt, doe all their endeuour to fly from that poyſon of papiſtrie, and without delay to ſhake of the yoke of that Antichriſt of Rome, that they may entirelie offer vp them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the ſeruice of this good Sauiour and Redeemer Ieſus Chriſt. And if ſo be, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the fellowſhippe which we haue with the Sonne of God, nor yet the promiſes of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie father can alure and induce vs to reſigne vp our ſoules and bodies vnto God, to put our affiance in him alone, to ſerue and to worſhip him alone, according to his good will &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but we will neuertheleſſe ſtick faſt to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, and ioyne right handes to perpetuall alliance with him, his miniſters, &amp; vpholders: yet let vs ſet before our eyes, to the end they may ſtrike deepelie into our hearts, &amp; we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by maie be driuen with feare from their perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious fellowſhip, the greeuous threatnings, and the heauie iudgment of God denounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs to that purpoſe, as namelie when he ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apoc.</hi> 18.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Depart out of Babylon my people, that yee be not partakers in her ſinnes, and that yee receiue not of her plagues.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apoc.</hi> 14.9.</note> Againe, <hi>If anie man worſhip the beast and his image, and receiue his marke in his forehead, or in his hand, the ſame ſhall drinke of the wine of the wrath of God, yea, of the pure wine, which is powred into the cuppe of wrath, and he ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be tormented in fire and brimstone before the holie
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6460:7"/>
Angels, and before the Lambe, and the ſmoke of their torment ſhall aſcend euermore: and they ſhall haue no rest day nor night, which worſhip the beaſt and his Image, and whoſoeuer receiueth the print of his name.</hi> And againe in another place,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.8.</note> 
                  <hi>But the fearefull and vnbeleeuers, and the abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and murtheres, and whoremongers, and ſorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and idolaters, and all liers, ſhall haue their part in the lake which burneth with fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, which is the ſecond death.</hi> Therefore let vs haue at the leaſt this poynt well printed in our hartes, to the end we be not led out of the way, and ſo for euer caſt away with the tymemen of this world, which ſuppoſe it is not a thing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible at once to ſerue both God &amp; the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, Ieſus Chriſt and Antichriſt, and to follow the commandements of God and of men, and to fulfill the affections of the fleſh and of the ſpirite.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>
                  <hi>OF REPENTANCE.</hi> The ſecond Article.</head>
               <p>THe former preparing of our ſelues in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of Faith, which applieth Ieſus Chriſt to vs in particular, with all his graces and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, can by no meanes haue anie place in our heartes, but it ſpeedilie begetteth in vs a true and vnfeigned repentance: that is, a true and earneſt loathing of that which is euill, and an ardent loue and affection towardes that which is good: which we ſee for our inſtruction in the examples of Dauid, Peter, Paul, and other
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6460:8"/>
holy perſonages. We muſt mourne inwardlie, euen in our bowels, &amp; ſorrow vnfeignedly that we haue offended the Maieſtie of God, that we haue moſt wickedli<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in former times abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed our creation, rede<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>on, &amp; baptiſme: that we haue prouoked G<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> anger in al the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of our bodie: that we haue abuſed our wit, our heart, our tongue, our feete and our hands: that we haue vnchaſtelie laide open our bodies and ſoules (which are the temples, wherein our God wil haue his abyding) to al kind of infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, idolatrie, filthineſſe, blaſphemie, whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, rauening, vſurie, theft, gluttonie, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennes, ambition, exceſſe, pride, and of all the other vanities of this world: which is in effect as much, as if we would haue God the Father, the Sonne, and the holie Ghoſt, to lodge in a baſe and vile backroome, full of deadly infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and filthie ſtinking. Wherefore we muſt be ſorie for our wicked life forepaſſed, calling our ſelues to a true and ſtrict accompt which may breede in our hearts an earneſt greife &amp; trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, that we haue in former times torne in peeces, and broken in all the partes thereof the lawe of God, to followe the will of the world, of the fleſh, &amp; of the deuil. The breaking of the bread in the Supper, ought not onelie to moue vs vnto the knowledge of our wickednes, but alſo to an abhomination thereof, being none other then whatſoeuer is to be found in vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant &amp; contrarie to the pure and holy lawe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6460:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of God. For whereas the bread is broken for vs, or rather we breake the bread of the ſupper of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, we are to learne, that it is we, that it is our ſinnes and iniquities, which haue crucified and <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to death the author of life, which is euen <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. And therefore we may not do as the infidels in times paſt, which made great lamentation, &amp; deuiſed ſharpe inuectiues againſt the Iewes, Pontius Pilate, Herod, Iudas, and thoſe that had executed and put to death Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; yet in the meane time flattered themſelues, gloried in their merites, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered not narrowlie, that Iudas, Pontius Pilate, and Herod were none other, then the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours and miniſters of their impieties and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Let vs conſider therefore in the breaking of the bread, that our ſinnes, yea the ſinnes of euerie one of vs in particular, haue crucified the Sonne of God, and haue broken him with the paines of the firſt and ſecond death: And euen ſo is it preciſelie witneſſed in the Supper, that the bodie of Ieſus Chriſt was broken for vs, and that his blood was ſhedde for the remiſſion of our ſinnes. And our heauenlie Father himſelfe doth teſtifie the ſame by the mouth of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Iſaiah, ſaying:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.</note> 
                  <hi>But he was wounded for our tranſgreſſions, he was broken for our iniquities.</hi> Now if it be ſo, that our ſinnes being weyed in the balance of God his iuſtice, are found to be of ſo gre<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t conſequence and importance, that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6460:9"/>
his anger and diſpleaſure conceiued againſt vs, can by no meanes be appeaſed, but by the death of his onelie Sonne, yea, by the cruel and ſhamefull death vpon the croſſe, by which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ſatiſfaction is per<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ed; why ſhould we not hencefoorth abhor<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ur ſinnes &amp; wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the cruell and bloodie murtherers of the onely Sonne of God? Behold, the Sunne &amp; the Moone, the elements, the vaile of the Temple, the ſtones &amp; rockes were mooued at the death of Ieſus Chriſt, and ſhewed tokens of ſorow &amp; heauineſſe; and ſhal not we, which beare about vs the cauſe of this death, abhorre ſo foule, euil-fauored, and vnfortunate a gueſt, who hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp his lodging in our heartes? and ſhall we ſuffer him to abide, or rather to dwel within vs, vntill he haue brought euerlaſting death into his lodging? No verely. But contrariwiſe we ought to eſteeme him moſt deteſtable, as one that firſt did ſet vp a wall of ſeparation between vs and God our ſouereigne happineſſe: and as one that hath cauſed vs to looſe that image and reſemblance of God, whereunto at the firſt we were created. It is he that hath defiled vs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and without: it is he that hath ſpoyled vs of our holines and righteouſnes: it is he that hath driuen &amp; chaſed vs out of Paradiſe: it is he that hath brought vs in bondage to the tyrany of the Deuil: it is he that hath made vs ſubiect to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie and ſickneſſe, and finally to the firſt and ſecond death: It is he, that after he had barred
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6460:9"/>
and diuided vs from God, cauſed vs to ſee our filthines, and brought vpon vs ſhame &amp; blacke reproch, that cauſed vs to tremble at the voice of our God, which before was to our eares moſt ſweete &amp; amiable. It is he, by whom the wrath of God is heaped vp againſt al mankind, which is in cauſe that the earth beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, and bringeth forth thorns and bryers, that women do labour and bring foorth children in ſorowe, and that men eate their bread with the ſweate of their face &amp; trauaile of their bodies. Now ſeeing that ſin doth bring vpon vs conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually ſo many euils &amp; miſchiefes, it followeth that we ought to retire &amp; withdraw our ſelues from it, except we will be voluntarie hinderers and enemies of our happines &amp; ſaluation. And heere I call into preſence al ſuch, as wallowing in al kind of ſinne and wickedneſſe, and giuing occaſion of grieuous offence to the children of God, are neuertheleſſe ſo ſhameleſſe, as they dare preſume to preſent themſelues at the Lord his table. I would haue them to anſwere, what it is that they promiſed to God, &amp; to his church in their Baptiſme? They wil ſaie; they promiſed to forſake the Deuill and al his works. Euen ſo: but ſinne is one of the cheife and principall workes of the Deuill: &amp; why then do they not abſtaine from it? why are they trayterous and diſloyal to God and to his Church? why haue they conſpired with the Deuil, the world, and the fleſh, againſt their owne ſaluation? how
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6460:10"/>
dare they preſent themſelues before God, to craue pardon &amp; remiſſion of their ſinnes at his hands, ſeeing that from time to time they doe heape ſinne vpon ſinne, and outragiouſlie cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie again, as much as in them lyeth, the Sonne of God, or at the leaſt deride the purgation of his blood, which was applyed to them in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme? Let the caſe be of an offendor, beggerly, needy, and deſtitute of al helpe &amp; ſuccour, that he were fallen into a fowle and filthie bogge, whereout by his owne ſtrength &amp; wit he could not eſcape, and of a King his ſonne paſſing by the ſaid place, that he tooke the paines to draw him out of this myrie hole, that he made him cleane, and that he decked him richlie with braue and coſtly attire. If this miſeralbe wretch ſhal returne againe into this pit of filth &amp; mire, defiling therein both his bodie &amp; his garments, and further, placing his life in extremity of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; maie we not iuſtlie thinke him to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankful aboue meaſure, and careleſſe of that princelie bountie and humilitie? On the other ſide, maie we not boldlie affirme, that he hath wittingly &amp; willingly taken an othe, as it were, againſt his owne life and ſafetie? and that he is worthy to come to ruine, and to periſh without al helpe and ſuccour? Like is the caſe betweene vs and Ieſus Chriſt. We are al fallen into the fowle pit of ſinne, in the perſon of Adam: we are al offendors before God, worthie of innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable gibets: we cannot of our ſelues by any
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6460:10"/>
meanes poſſible get out of this pit of our deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, into the which we are fallen by our owne defaulte and follie. The Sonne of God, the King of Kings, the Lord of Lords, not onelie draweth vs out of this filthy pit, but waſheth vs cleane alſo with his pretious blood, &amp; vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafeth to cloath vs with his owne garment of righteouſneſſe &amp; innocencie. If we fall to tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and to wallow againe in the pit of ſinne, if we pleaſe our ſelues therein, if we defile and ſtayne the garment of innocencie, which he gaue vs in Baptiſme cleane and vnſpotted; do we not manifeſtlie contemne the loue and the benefit of Ieſus Chriſt not able no be valued &amp; eſteemed? &amp; are we not worthie to rot an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand times in our vncleanneſſe, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Deuill in hell to gnaſh our teeth for euer? It is out of al controuerſie. Then ſith it is ſo, that the end of our redemption, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, &amp; iuſtification, requireth that we ſhould abſtaine from ſinne (ſo farre as is poſſible, and the fraylenes of mans nature can permit) it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooueth vs to employ al our paine &amp; diligence by the mightie power of the Spirit of God, to driue out of our ſoules &amp; bodies al vncleannes, filthines, idolatrie, blaſphemie, rebellion, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, murther, whoredome, ſtealing, vſurie, and al other things contrarie to his holy law, vnleſſe we wil be vnthankefull towards Ieſus Chriſt, and open enemies to his Church, and to our owne ſaluation.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:6460:11"/>Now, becauſe it is not ſufficient, to the end we may be endued with true repentance, that we know our ſins, that we abhorre them, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe them, &amp; abſtaine from them; but we muſt alſo know, deſire, and do that which is good, as we are charged in the word of God: We are to looke narrowly to thoſe reaſons, whereby we ought to be ſtirred vp to ſanctifie the name of God. Firſt, whereas we are ioyned and knit to Ieſus Chriſt in the ſupper; whereas we are made fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bone; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as we liue by his holy Spirit: ought not theſe things to moue vs to faſhion our ſelues after the image and likenes of our Lord and Sauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt? Can he dwell in vs? can he feede vs with his owne ſubſtance? can he quicken vs with his Spirit? can he ioyne vs vnto himſelfe, and tye vs with the linkes of Faith, and yet ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he, nor the holy Ghoſt, nor Faith ſhal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile with vs to the bringing forth of good and holy workes &amp; actions? Further, ſeeing it is ſo, that he giueth not himſelf vnto vs by the halfe, neither yet voyd of his moſt excellent qualities and treaſures, but garded with al ſpiritual gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and bleſſings, adorned with righteouſneſſe and perfection, hauing innocencie and holines in his traine: how is it poſſible we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue Ieſus Chriſt enritched with al his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, but that the righteouſneſſe of our head muſt ſhine in vs which are his members? yea in euery of our parts, whither they be of the ſoule
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6460:11"/>
inward, or of the bodie outward. Is it meete, that the partes of our ſoule, which are two in number, to wit, our vnderſtanding &amp; our wil, which ought to laie hold vpon the promiſes of God, which ought by Faith to receiue the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and blood of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that is to ſaie, Ieſus Chriſt al and ſome, very God, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall in al poynts to God his Father, and verie man, compounded of humane ſoule and body; is it meete (I ſaie) that theſe, our vnderſtanding and wil, ſhould be applied to the meditation of worldly and wicked things, and ſhould be void of the knowledge and loue of God, and of due charitie towards our neighbour? Is it meete, that our bodie, which is the Temple of God, ſhould be prophaned and made vnholie? that our eares, which God created, to the end we might heare his voice, ſhould be ſtopped at the ſounding of the heauenlie voyce, and open at the burſting foorth of vaine and wanton talke, of vnchaſt ſongs and lewd ſonnets? Is it meet, that our tongue, which is bound by the lawe of creation to ſing out the praiſe of God, and by the law of redemption to preach the tydings of the Lords death vntil his comming; is it meet, Iſaie, that this tongue, ſo fit an inſtrument to God his glorie, ſhould be mute in al good oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, and looſe to backebyte, to ſlaunder, to blaſpheame without ceaſing, or, at the leaſt, moſt ſlipperie to caſt out idle words, for the which we ſhall one daie giue accompt before
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6460:12"/>
the throne of God his Maieſtie? Is it meet, that our mouth, which receiueth the ſacred ſigne of the body and blood of Ieſus Chriſt, ſhould ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the benefit of our redemption, and that the poyſon of aſpes ſhould lurcke within our lippes? Is it meet, that our hands, which laye holde in the ſupper vpon the aſſured gage of God his loue, of the league which he hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred with vs, and of our ſaluation, ſhould not onely be heauy to do good, but alſo nimble to ſpoyle, to ſteale, to murther, to oppreſſe, and to vſe violence? Is it meet, that our feete, which ought to runne to al good actions, ſhould be ready and ſwift to runne after euil? No certein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie: neither is it tolerable in any condition. But <hi>Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he which calleth vs is holy, ſo ought we,</hi> both inwardly and outwardly, <hi>to ſhine with holineſſe.</hi> As he by holy Baptiſme hath brought vs into his holy houſe, which is the holy Church, the communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Saincts: ſo we ought in the ſame Church to lead a godly life, and to be of an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conuerſation. As he hath waſhed our ſinnes away by the precious blood of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt: ſo ought we to die vnto ſin, and to liue vnto righteouſnes. As he hath called vs to a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer dying or decaying hope of a bleſſed reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; life euerlaſting: ſo ought we to lift vp our hearts on high, &amp; not to be buried like moales in this frayle and tranſitorie earth, which with al things aboue &amp; vnder it is ſure to vaniſh. To be ſhort,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11.</note> ſeeing <hi>the grace of God is offered vnto vs</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:6460:12"/>
from day to day, and his holy word ſoundeth in our eares continually for this end onely, that <hi>the ſame may bring ſaluation vnto vs, and that we denying vngodlineſſe and worldly luſts, ſhould lead a ſober, righteous, and godly life in this preſent world, looking for the bleſſed hope and appearing of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the mighty God, &amp; of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> we muſt praie vnto God, that by his grace we may ſo carrie our ſelues towards him in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſo towards our neighbour in righteouſnes, and ſo toward our ſelues in ſobernes, that we maie be found vnblameable at the great &amp; ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible day of the Lord, by the meane of the ſame his welbeloued Sonne, our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>
                  <hi>OF THANKSGIVING.</hi> The third Article.</head>
               <p>Thirdlie it is requiſite, that we bee hartelie thankfull to God for the exceeding bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of our redemption. For to the end was the holie ſupper called <hi>Eucharistia,</hi> that is to ſaie, a thankſgiuing. And ſurelie <hi>if our meates,</hi> and the dailie bread which God giueth vs for the foode &amp; nouriſhment of our bodies, <hi>ought to be ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the word, &amp; receiued with giuing of thanks:</hi> is it not our partes, ſo much the rather to giue God thanks, for the heauenlie bread, and for nouriſhment of our ſoules offered and giuen effectuallie vnto vs in the holy ſupper? yea, that which ought to be vnto vs a notable prouoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we ſee that our Sauiour himſelfe hath by
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6460:13"/>
his owne example declared vnto vs our duetie in this behalfe. <hi>For when he tooke the bread,</hi> S. Mathew and S. Marke record, <hi>that he bleſſed it before he brake it and gaue it to his diſciples</hi> which word of <hi>bleſſing</hi> S. Luke expoundeth to be <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of thanks.</hi> Now ſeeing that Ieſus Chriſt when he tooke the bread, gaue thanks to God his father, which he did in like manner when he tooke the cuppe, and all for the redeeming of mankind: is it not a principal &amp; chiefe point of our duety, to render like thanks, ſeeing it is we onelie which receiue ſo great and excellent a benefite? But to the end we may be the better mooued and ſtirred vp to this acceptable ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of thankſgiuing, it behooueth vs to thinke vpon the worthineſſe of the benefite of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and vpon that moſt excellent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent which God beſtoweth vppon vs at this holy Table: which cannot be done except we enter into a deepe &amp; due conſideration of our miſerable eſtate and condition, a ſigne where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was long ſithens expreſſed vnto vs in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall captiuitie and bondage of Gods people in Egipt. We ſee there, how Pharoh was ſtrong and mightie, how he knewe not the Almighty, how hee pretended to put to death the whole ſtock and ſeed of the Iſraelites by the ſuppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and cutting ſhort of the male children. We ſee alſo how he enioyned the Hebrews to labor exceſſiue &amp; vnreaſonable, yea without all hope of anie wages or reward: how he would not
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6460:13"/>
ſuffer them to offer ſacrifice vnto the Lord, nor to depart out of the land of Egipt. And this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion continued not for one yeare or two, but by the ſpace of fowre hundred &amp; thirty yeares: wherein we maie clearelie behold the liuelie picture and reſemblance of our moſt wretched and miſerable eſtate. We were all loſt in Adam, and brought to ruine &amp; deſtruction. We were retayned captiues in the infernall Egypt, vnder the tyrannie of the ſpirituall Pharaoh, which is the Deuill. This tyrant was ſtong and mightie: hee would not ſuffer vs to ſerue our God: he made vs to take an endleſſe and reſtleſſe labour in the ſeruile and fruitleſſe workes of ſinne, for the eſtabliſhing of his kingdome: he ſlew not onelie our male children, but caried vs al with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out anie difference into euerlaſting deſtruction of bodie and ſoule. Which tyrannie had not continued and endured onelie for a ſhort ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but had bene euen in a prooued ſtrength and fulnes for euer, if we had not bene thence deliuered by the power and mercy of our God, through the miniſtrie and meane of that true Moyſes, our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the true lambe deliuered as it were into the iawes of death, that we might bee ſaued and obtaine eternall life. For ſo it is plainely teſtified in the ſcripture, that <hi>God ſo loued the world, that he gaue his onelie begotten ſonne, to the end that whoſoeuer beleeued in him, ſhould not periſh but haue euerlaſting life.</hi> Now ſeing that God hath bene ſo bountifull
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6460:14"/>
and mercifull vnto vs, that he hath ſet vs at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie from the tyranie of the Deuill, of ſinne, of death, and of hel: ſeing that his loue towards vs hath bene ſo wonderfull, that he hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered his onelie ſonne to endure a cruell and ſhamefull death, to deliuer vs which wear ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants and bondſlaues to the deuill: his welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, for vs which were his enemies: the righteous and the lambe without ſpot, for vs which were ſinfull and altogether corrupted: the onelie inheritour of heauen, for vs the true and lawfull heires of hell: ought we not to be rauiſhed with an admiration of this won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull and vnutterable loue of our God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs? and to haue our tongues continually vnfolded and vntied to chaunt out with loud &amp; cleare voice the praiſe of this benefite of our redemption? Let vs remember that Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe doth put vs in minde of our duetie in this behalfe, when he ſaith touching the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brating of his holie Supper, <hi>Do this in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of me.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24.</note> And S. Paul expoundeth this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, where he giueth vs to vnderſtand that <hi>as often as we ſhall eat this bread and drinke this cuppe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26.</note> 
                  <hi>we ſhew the Lords death vntill his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</hi> Then ſith it is ſo, that God requireth at our handes a true and vnfeigned acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of thoſe benefites which we receiue of his bountie and largenes, by the meane of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt; let vs be well aduiſed, that we be not ſpotted or infected with
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6460:14"/>
the vice of ingratitude, except we wil incur the wrath and heauy diſpleaſure of God, &amp; ſo finde him a ſharpe &amp; ſeuere iudge, whom we would not acknowledge a louing, gentle, &amp; pitiful fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: to which purpoſe S. Paul threatneth al vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankful, where he ſaith, <hi>Whoſoeuer ſhall eate this bread, &amp; drink the cup of the Lord vnworthily,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhalbe guiltie of the body &amp; blood of the Lord.</hi> and ſoone after in the ſame Chap. <hi>He that eateth &amp; drinketh vnworthily, eateth &amp; drinketh his owne damnation.</hi> And ſurely it ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth with good reaſon that the vengeance of God is diſcharged vpon al thoſe which wickedly ſuppreſſe the glorie of God, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in that thing which concerneth their own ſaluation. For if a theefe being now in the hands of the hangman for felonnie whereof he was iuſtly &amp; lawfully co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned, reiecting the Prince his free pardon &amp; grace, and not vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafing to thank him for the ſame, is wel worthy to be diſpatched with expedition: or if a child which daylie and howerly receiueth of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all things neceſſarie for his life and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and hath not once in his mouth the word of kindneſſe, I thanke you father, is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be beaten with many ſtripes: how much more are we, which for our manifold and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious offences and treſpaſſes haue iuſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued to be hanged vp in hell, when we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne and ſet at naught the grace and fauour of God our ſouereigne Prince, &amp; make no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of the eternal bleſſings, which he giueth
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6460:15"/>
vs in Chriſt, offered vnto vs in the holy Supper: how much more (I ſaie) are we worthy to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh for our vnthankfulneſſe, ſo fowle and odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a ſinne before God and man? Now concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this matter of thankfulneſſe, theſe poynts following are to be diligentlie regarded &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued. Firſt, we muſt make this recogniſance to God alone, by his onely Sonne our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. For euen as God by his Sonne alone hath created &amp; redeemed vs from euerlaſting death: ſo he would haue vs to render thankes to him alone for al his benefits, &amp; that by his onely Sonne in whom he is well pleaſed. This we may learne of S. Paul in many places, &amp; ſpecially in his Epiſt. to the Ephe. where it is written in this wiſe.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.3.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed be God euen the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord Ieſus Christ, which hath bleſſed vs with all ſpiritual bleſſing in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly things in Chriſt, as he hath choſen vs in him before the foundation of the world.</hi> Then they that call vppon Saincts, that put their truſt in them or to their merites: they that make them the patrones and aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates of their cauſes: alſo they that are repoſed vpon their owne ſtrength, free will, or good works, do manifeſtly rob God of his glorie, and cannot truely performe the giuing of thankes for the ſingular benefite of their redemption. For we cannot attribute to any creature, be it neuer ſo little in the matter of our ſaluation, but we ſhalbe culpable of treaſon in the higheſt degree againſt the maieſtie of our maker. And
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6460:15"/>
therefore, let vs, renouncing our ſelues and all the creatures of God in the whole or in part, ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>Now vnto the king euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, immortall, inuiſible, vnto God onely wiſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17.</note> 
                  <hi>be honor and glorie for euer and euer. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, this giuing of thankes muſt not onely ſound out of the mouth, but it muſt alſo proceed from the heart. For ſeeing that God is a Spirite, he requireth of vs ſuch a kinde of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice as is fitlie anſwerable to his nature, that is to ſay, he will be worſhiped and ſerued of vs in Spirit and truth. And therefore when we ſhall be occaſioned to praiſe God for the benefite of redemption, we muſt haue our hearts erected: that there may be a ſweete agreement and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall accord betweene our affections within, and our tongue without, as we ſee that Dauid exhorted himſelfe to this manner of ſeruing and praiſing God. <hi>My ſoule,</hi> ſaith he,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1.</note> 
                  <hi>praiſe thou the Lord, and all that is within me, praiſe his holie name. My ſoule praiſe thou the Lord, and forget not all his benefites.</hi> And the holie Virgin ſingeth the ſame notes, <hi>My ſoule doth magnifie the Lord, and my ſpirite reioyceth in God my Sauiour.</hi> Then we may hereby vnderſtand, that all hypocrites and diſſemblers, and all thoſe that ſing &amp; praiſe God in an vnknowen language are heere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued for their ſeruice. For without vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding there can neither be affection, nor wil, nor conſequently Faith, without the which what duetie ſo euer we performe to God, beare
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6460:16"/>
it neuer ſo faire a colour in appearance to the eyes of men, is ſinne abhominable in the eyes of God. Then let vs take heede that we be not taken halting in this point, leſt we be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the people of the Iewes, which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiped and ſerued God in vaine,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 29.13.</note> becauſe <hi>They came neere vnto him onely with their tongue, and honored him with their lippes, but their hearts were farre from him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, this duety is at al times to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that is to ſaie, as wel in time of aduerſitie, as in time of proſperitie.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.1.</note> To which purpoſe the Prophet Dauid proteſteth, that <hi>He will alwaie giue thankes vnto the Lord: and that his praiſe ſhall be in his mouth continually.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.18.</note> And S. Paul admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the Theſſalonians <hi>To giue thankes in all things,</hi> with this addition, <hi>For this is the wil of god in Christ Ieſus.</hi> This precept is greatly contrary to our tymemen, &amp; to al ſuch as court the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel in time of proſperitie, &amp; are then right glad and eaſilie entreated to praiſe the Lord, whom afterward in time of aduerſitie they curſſe and diſhonour. The cauſe of this miſchiefe is, for that they came not to be of the Church for any true end and good purpoſe, as namely, to exalt the glorie of God, to procure their ſaluation with the ſaluation of their brethren: but rather to become great and mightie in poſſeſſions &amp; honorable places, &amp; to ſatiſfie their owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate and particular humors. Whereupon it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe, that ſo ſoone as the deuill lifteth
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6460:16"/>
vp his hornes againſt the church of God, and that perſecution is at hand, immediatlie they melt away in affliction as wax before the fire, they are offended, they are dried vp &amp; parched in the ſunne of the croſſe, they are ſorie for all the good which they haue doone, and repent they haue bene caried with ſo haſtie a ſwinge, to confeſſe the name of the lord Ieſus Chriſt in the aſſemblie of the faithfull: they would they had neuer knowne either God, or his word, or his church, or his miniſters: becauſe they ſett more by a meſſe of potage as Eſau did,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.38.</note> then by the birthright and bleſſing of the heauenlie Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But let this kind of people knowe, that it ſhal no more profite them, then it auailed Cain, Eſau, Saul, and Iudas to haue made a good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and as it were to haue lifted vp their ſheild and target luſtilie at the firſt in the Lords quarrell. For ſeeing the ſentence is generall, <hi>Whoſoeuer perſeuereth and continueth to the end, he ſhall be ſaued:</hi> it followeth on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, that all ſuch as hold not out conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in the confeſſion of the ſonne of God, and ſuch as ſhalbe let and hindred by their worldlie goods and poſſeſſions, by offices of honour, by the loue of the world, by the eaſe of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, from confeſſing and acknowledging as it were in one and the ſame a continual vaine, the worthie benefite of their redemption: I ſaie, it foloweth that ſuch ſhall periſh euerlaſtinglie.</p>
               <p>Laſtlie, it is to be noted, that we maie not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6460:17"/>
onely acknowledge Gods benefites when we are alone, but alſo when we are aſſembled in publike places, euen in the face and preſence of the whole congregation. And therefore ſaith Dauid,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.12</note> 
                  <hi>What ſhal I render vnto the Lord for all his benefits towards me? I will take the cup of ſaluation, and call vpon the name of the Lord. I will paie my vowes vnto the Lord, euen now in the preſence of all his people.</hi> Alſo in another place. <hi>I haue declared thy righteouſnes in the great congregation:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.9.</note> 
                  <hi>loe, I will not refraine my lips, O Lord, thou knowest. I haue not hid thy righteouſnes within mine hart, but I haue declared thy truth and thy ſaluation: I haue not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed thy mercie and thy truth from the great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.</hi> This is a thing to be deeply imprinted in the hearts of al ſuch as are yet but weak, and of al thoſe that are aſhamed to confeſſe and to praiſe our Lord Ieſus Chriſt in open &amp; publique meetings. For ſeeing that God doth openly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouch vs for his people, &amp; giueth himſelf freely to vs &amp; to our children in the perſon of his wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued Son our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, we can do no leſſe then aduouch him publiquely for our God and Sauiour, in the perſon of the ſame his deare ſonne our Lord Ieſus Chriſt?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>
                  <hi>OF CHARITIE.</hi> The fourth Article.</head>
               <p>FAith, Repentance, &amp; Thankſgiuing to God, can haue no place in our hearts and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and it is to no purpoſe that we are called Chriſtians, or that we brag &amp; vaunt of the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6460:17"/>
of the commandements conteined in the firſt Table co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the ſeruice of God aboue mentioned, except we ſhew the effects &amp; fruits thereof in keeping the commandements of the ſecond Table, which touch our charitable affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction towards our neighbour, without the which we cannot come worthily to the holie Supper. To this end and purpoſe, Ieſus Chriſt in that Sermon of the Supper, which he made to his Apoſtles that verie night when he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traied &amp; deliuered vp to death for vs, diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put them in remembrance of this leſſon. <hi>By this ſhal all men knowe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that you are my Diſciples, if yee haue loue one to another.</hi> Alſo,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 13.35. <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.12.</note> 
                  <hi>This is my commaundement, that yee loue one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, as I haue loued you.</hi> To the ſame ende alſo tendeth that action of our Sauiour, when he waſhed his Apoſtles feete the ſame night: after which waſhing hee ſaide vnto them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Know ye what I haue done to you? ye call me maſter, and Lord, and ye ſay well: for ſo am I. If I then,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.12.</note> 
                  <hi>your Lord and Maſter, haue waſhed your feete: ye alſo ought to waſh one anothers feete. for I haue giuen you an example, that ye ſhould do, euen as I haue done to you.</hi> We muſt therefore according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement and example of the ſonne of God; haue a careful regard that we be furniſhed with a true &amp; an ardent affection towards our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, if we will come worthely to the holy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of our Lord. And if any man aske a deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Charitie, to know the better what
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6460:18"/>
it is, he may go to S. Paul, who hath painted it out in verie liuely &amp; beautifull colours, writing to the Corinthians, after this manner. <hi>Loue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth long: it is bountifull: loue enuyeth not: loue doth not boaſt it ſelfe: it is not puffed vp: it diſdai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not: it ſeeketh not her owne things: it is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked to anger: it thinketh not euill: it reioyceth not in iniquitie, but reioyceth in the truth: it ſuffereth all things: it beleeueth al things: it hopeth al things: it endureth all things:</hi> This is the charitie which we ought to haue, &amp; to vſe towards our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: the ſeuerall parts whereof we muſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently prouide that we can be able to fetch out of our owne boſoms. And to this we are diuerſe &amp; ſundrie waies exhorted in the Supper of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Firſt, whereas it is our dutie to ſtay one for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and it is not lawfull for euery one of vs to receiue the Supper ſingle, but when the whole congregation is aſſembled, al the faithful toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do take<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; eate, and drinke, the bread &amp; the wine of the Supper, according to the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of Ieſus Chriſt, ſaying, <hi>Take, eate, drinke ye al of this:</hi> it is a certeine token &amp; witneſſe that we ought to be all vnited &amp; knit together. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whereas we being all met in one and the ſelfe ſame houſe of God, which is his Church, we all do there together call vpon one and the ſelfe ſame father which is in heauen, we haue al one and the ſelfe ſame head, aduocate, &amp; inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour which is Ieſus Chriſt: whereas we do al
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6460:18"/>
heare one &amp; the ſelfſame word of God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as we do all eate one and the ſelfe ſame ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual meate, &amp; do al drink one and the ſelfe ſame ſpiritual drinke: and whereas we all as brethren lay claime to one and the ſelfe ſame inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which is the kingdome of heauen: ought we not to be ſtirred vp and inflamed hereby to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie an vnfeigned &amp; an earneſt affection one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another? Laſtly, the very making of that bread &amp; wine which is vſed in the Supper, doth teach vs what vnion &amp; concord of hearts and minds there ought to be betweene vs the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of one and the ſame heauenly father. For euen as we ſee that the bread is made of diuerſe cornes, which neuertheleſſe is but one loafe: &amp; as the wine is made of many grapes, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe, when it is made, is but one wine: ſo ought all Chriſtians which in themſelues are manie, to be vnited by loue in one body, which is the Church, whereof Ieſus Chriſt is to be the ſole head, &amp; captaine. Then we muſt note that this loue, wherunto we are exhorted in the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per by ſo many arguments, is abſent where men are infected with hatred, ſtrife, rancor, debate, factions, &amp; with hote ſutes to the hinderance of their brethren. and therfore before we come to this Supper, which is a witneſſe of our vniting as well with Ieſus Chriſt, as with his Church, if there be any ſtrife or quarrel betweene vs &amp; our brethren, we muſt in all good and amiable ſort be reconciled: if we haue bin offended, we muſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6460:19"/>
freely &amp; frankly forgiue our brethren, yea our enemies: as we would haue God to forgiue vs, and as we ſee that our Lord Ieſus Chriſt left vs an example of this loue and charitie, when he prayed to God his father for his enemies which put him to a cruel death: whereof Sainct Steuen alſo giueth vs a godly example. Alſo it is to be noted, that this loue is to be practiſed of all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates: as wel of kings who are to loue their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, to be nources for the church of God, to be louers of the publique peace of the land, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat their ſubiects gently &amp; moderately: as alſo of the people whoſe part is to honour the king, to pay their tributes truly &amp; faithfully, to obey all his Liuetena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; his officers. It is the ſheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds dutie to loue his flock, to watch, to labor, and to pray for it without ceaſing. Alſo it is the part of the ſheepe to loue their ſheepeherd: of fathers to loue their children, of childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to loue their fathers &amp; mothers: of the wife to loue her huſband, &amp; of the husband to loue his wife: of maſters to loue their ſeruants, and of ſeruants to loue their maſters: and laſtly it behooueth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one of vs for his particular part, to exerciſe charitie in that vocation wherin God hath pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him in his eternall prouidence and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. For otherwiſe we ſhall neuer be able faithfully to acquite vs of our duetie as well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God as towards men, except we be gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and gouerned by the rule of charitie, in all our affaires and buſineſſe whatſoeuer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:6460:19"/>
               <head>Neceſsarie obſeruations for all thoſe that deſire to come to the Lord his Table.</head>
               <p>THus we haue vnderſtood, wherin the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining &amp; proouing of our ſelues co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth: wherunto is to be added a good aduiſement &amp; due conſideration of the points &amp; obſeruations following. Firſt we muſt take good heede, that we be not ouer buſie in making a curious ſearch of the life of another: following the ſteppes of many, which ſift ſo narrowly the imperfections of their brethren, that in the meane while their owne infirmities are vtterly forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wel may we pray, yea we ought to procure with all our power &amp; ability, that the church may be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued &amp; kept in puritie, &amp; altogether without ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or ſhew of any offence. But forſomuch as in this world, the corne ſhalbe always ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the chaffe, the good fiſh with the bad, Iudas with the true Apoſtles, the fooliſh virgins with the wiſe: it is not meet that any of vs ſhold haſtely take offence thereat, but contrariwiſe that he endeuor to find that perfection in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, which he ſeeketh to bring into another.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we may not thinke that Faith, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, thankeſgiuing, &amp; loue, and the other vertues, which God requireth at our hands, can be perfect in vs during this mortal life. For there wil be alwaies to be found in vs, be we neuer ſo thorowlie and perfectlie renued, ſome reliques of ſinne, of vnbeliefe, of impenitencie, of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſſe, and of ſelfeloue: which al are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6460:20"/>
contrarie and manifeſtlie oppoſed to the loue of our neighbour. So long as we liue, <hi>there is a law in our members, which rebelleth againſt the lawe of our minde:</hi> the Deuill and the world will riſe vp againſt vs in battaile, as we may ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entlie be inſtructed by the liues of the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, Prophets, and Apoſtles: yea, euen vntill our laſt breathing we ſhal haue need to praie vnto God, that it may pleaſe him to forgiue our hourelie ſinnes thorough his Sonne, our onelie Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. But yet, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections and iniquities abyding in vs, ought to preuayle ſo litle to the withdrawing of our ſeues from God, that if we be heartely ſory and grieued for the ſame, they ſhould rather cauſe vs to draw neere vnto him, &amp; to this holy ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, to the end that, like miſerable ſtarued cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures, we might receiue Ieſus Chriſt with the more greedineſſe, who is the true and onelie foode and nouriſhment of our ſoules.</p>
               <p>Thirdlie, albeit a perfect Faith, repentance, giuing of thankes, and loue, is not neceſſary to the end we may come worthilie to the Supper: yet they muſt be al true, &amp; not counterfeit; they muſt come from the heart, and from the ſpirit. Our Faith may not be feigned, our repentance may not be diſſembled, as is the manner of the hypocites: the thankes which we giue to God, may not proceede onely out of the mouth: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt we loue our brethren onelie in word, &amp; not in deed: but the whole profeſſion of our
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6460:20"/>
Faith &amp; Chriſtian life, muſt aboue all things be farre remooued from vayne boaſting and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling, that we may take more care &amp; paines to be effectualy &amp; before God, then to be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med &amp; taken for good Chriſtians before men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Against thoſe that wittingly and willingly absteine from the Lord his Supper.</head>
               <p>AS they are many which faulte in comming vnworthily to the Supper: ſo there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie which offend of the contrarie, namelie, in not comming at al, nor preſenting themſelues to the ſaid holy banquet: fearing (as they ſaie) to be partakers of the ſame vnworthilie, and ſo conſequently, to be culpable and guiltie of the bodie and blood of Ieſus Chriſt. But let them knowe, which abſteine of ſet purpoſe from the table of the Lord, that it is no leſſe a vice, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough vnthankfulnes and contempt of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meates, which God ſetteth before vs in the Supper, to abſtaine, then it is to receiue it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily: euen as the patient which is daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly ſicke, if he make no accompt of the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition his receipt and order, deſerueth no leſſe blame then he that abuſeth the ſame receipt &amp; dyet, and doth not vſe it with diſcretion &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration according as it was ordered by the Phyſition. And let them not therefore abuſe &amp; flatter themſelues, as if hereby they might e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape vnblameable before God and men, ſeing it is a caſe moſt cleare, &amp; a thing moſt certeine, that ſo groſſe vnthankfulneſſe cannot be cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6460:21"/>
nor by any meanes poſſible beare excuſe. For firſt, they wittingly deſpiſe the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Ieſus Chriſt, who ſaith to al that be his, <hi>Doe this, take, and eate.</hi> Secondly, they ſet light by the happie memory of the death and paſſion of the Sonne of God, who ſaith to the faithfull, that they ſhal celebrate and keepe ſolemne the ſupper <hi>in remembrance of him.</hi> Thirdly, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne the price of their redemption, to wit, the precious bodie &amp; blood of Ieſus Chriſt, which are giuen and parted to al true Chriſtians in the Supper, as it is written: <hi>This is my body, which is giuen for you, this is my blood which is ſhed for the remiſſion of your ſinnes.</hi> Laſtly, they deſpiſe the Church, and the vnion thereof, &amp; of their owne accord excommunicate themſelues from the fellowſhip that the faithful haue in the Supper, as well with Ieſus Chriſt, as one with another. Thus we ſee, that theſe contemners of the Lord his Supper, do groſſely falt and grieuouſly ſinne in this behalfe, and are altogether void and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of excuſe. Let vs therefore take heede that we follow not their example, except we wil run into the like danger with them that for their oxen, fermes, wiues, and trafficke of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe refuſed to come to the mariage in the Goſpel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of them that come vnworthily to the holie Supper of the Lord, and ought not to be admitted.</head>
               <p>Of them that ſinne againſt the firſt Article of the firſt preparation, which conſiſteth in true faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:6460:21"/>AL Atheiſts, vnbeleeuers, &amp; ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God &amp; of his word, al heretickes, and falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, all magitians, idolaters, and ſuperſtitious perſons which are partakers of the table of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils: Furthermore, al ſuch as haue but an hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal faith: al the adherents &amp; miniſters of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt of Rome, &amp; al ſuch as any way eſtabliſh his kingdome, or depend thereupon: all ſuch as are not yet brought to be of the number of the church of God, &amp; haue not made profeſſion of their faith: finally al ſuch as make it but an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon matter to ſweare by the name of God, or by their faith, &amp; apply the ſame to vaine &amp; fruteles matters: al ſuch, I ſay, may not preſume to touch the holy table of the Lord, becauſe they haue not true affiance and truſt in God, without the which we can not be mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; ſo conſequently can not be fit &amp; able to receiue life of him, who is the onelie head and cheife of al the faithfull.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of thoſe that ſinne againſt the ſecond article of the ſecond preparation, which conſiſteth of Repentance.</head>
               <p>AL ſuch as lead an odious, an impudent, &amp; a looſe life, all the contemners of God, of his word, &amp; of his holy congregation: all they that deny and blaſpheme the name of God: all ſuch as contemne the correction &amp; diſcipline of the church: againe, they that ordinarely fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent &amp; haunt euill company: they that walke in the councell of the vngodly, that ſtand in the way of ſinners, or ſit in the cheare of the ſcorne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful:
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6460:22"/>
finally that giue no hope of amendment of life, or of renewing of their minds: that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit outragious, groſſe, infamous, &amp; monſterous ſinnes, ſuch as are puniſhable by the ciuil magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, al theſe, I ſay, being knowen to be of ſo fowle a race, may not be admitted to this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: and if they offer themſelues, they are to be refuſed, leaſt that which is holy be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to dogs, and to ſwine, to the great diſhonor of God, and offence to the Church and Congregation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of thoſe that ſinne againſt the third article of the third pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration which conſiſteth in thankeſgiuing.</head>
               <p>WIthout true faith &amp; vnfeigned repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be meet to publiſh the praiſes of God, which wil not be praiſed out of the mouth of the wicked &amp; vngodly: wherfore all they that are voyd and deſtitute of faith, of knowledg &amp; of repentance, do alſo ſin againſt this article, and ought not to be receiued at the Lords table. They alſo that are bereft of their wittes, &amp; fooliſh by nature, or by accident: they that being vnder age, as litle children, can not ſhew forth the Lords death vntil his comming; are al vncapable of his ſupper. Finally they that through weakeneſſe, vnthankfulnes, &amp; want of taking knowledge of Gods benefits, haue in the troubleſome and heauy times of aduerſitie forſaken Gods cauſe &amp; quarrell, and haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the name of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, ought not to haue acceſſe vnto his holy table, before they haue made confeſſion of their fault
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6460:22"/>
in publique, and be reconciled to the Church of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of thoſe that ſinne against the fourth article of the fourth preparation, which conſisteth in Charitie towardes our neighbour.</head>
               <p>AL ſuch as are diſobedient to fathers, &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to the magiſtrate, &amp; to al ſuperiours: alſo all ſeditious perſons, fighters, murtheres, &amp; ſuch as beare hatred or malice againſt their neighbour: they that are poſſeſſed &amp; carried with a ſpirit of reuenging: whoremongers, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulteres, vnchaſt, geuen to vnnaturall luſt &amp; vncleanes, drunkards, gluttones, ful of deceit, of couetouſnes, of theft, of vſury: backebiters, ſkorners, falſe witneſſes, lyars, men conuicted of common periurie, and generaly all ſuch as make a trade &amp; occupation of abuſing the loue of our neighbour, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined in the ſecond table of the lawe of God, are to be excluded out of the nomber of the faithful to whome it belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to be preſent at this holy &amp; ſpiritual feaſt. For ſeing the Scriptures pronounce &amp; teſtifie that ſuch haue no felowſhip with the Lorde, that they are ſhut out of the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, &amp; that they ſhal not reſt vpon the holy hill of the Lorde: they ought by great reaſon to be barred from thoſe holy ſinges, by the whiche the faithfull are ioyned to Chriſt, &amp; made poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſours of euerlaſting life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="dialogue">
               <pb facs="tcp:6460:23"/>
               <head>A DIALOGVE WHEREIN WE are taught how we ſhould come to the holy Supper of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Father.</speaker>
                  <p>HOw muſt we be prepared, when we come to the Lord his table, that we may be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy receiuers of his holy Supper?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Child.</speaker>
                  <p>We muſt examine our ſelues diligently, as we are warned by S. Paul in his Epiſtle to the Corinthians.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>In how many points lyeth this triall &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of our ſelues?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Verily in two points. Firſt, that we carrie our ſelues towards God, who calleth &amp; biddeth vs to this holy banquet, as he hath ordeined in his commandements, and as we are bound by our obedience: Secondly, that we haue regard of our behauiour &amp; bearing towardes our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, which are no leſſe bidden nor welcome gueſts, then we, to this holy Banquet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>What is required in regard of our duetie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>There be three points, which are principal and heads to many other, wherein this our due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie towards God is founded.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Rehearſe thoſe three points wherein prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally this duetie ſtandeth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>The firſt is Faith: the next Repentance: and the laſt Thankeſgiuing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>What is Faith?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>It is a firme &amp; faſt perſwaſion, or a certeine aſſurance, that God is our Father and Sauiour, in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6460:23"/>
the name of his Sonne our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Doth this Faith ſpring out of our hearts as out of the founteine?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>we are not the authors thereof:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.13.</note> but <hi>it is the gift of God,</hi> for <hi>the faithfull are not borne of fleſh nor of blood, nor of the will of man, but of God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>What be the meanes which God vſeth to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get vs vnto him, and to endue vs with Faith?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>None other then his holy and heauenly worde,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn.</hi> 17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>Galat.</hi> 4.</note> eſtabliſhed and confirmed in vs by the mightie working of <hi>his holy Spirite, which crieth in our hearts, Abba, that is to ſay Father.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Is not this Faith made firme and warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in vs by the Lords Supper?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>It muſt needes be ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> firſt our Faith is ſigned &amp; ſealed in the Supper in this reſpect, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Ieſus Chriſt giueth himſelfe vnto vs,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. <hi>Mark.</hi> 14. <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 21.</note> aſſuring vs that <hi>his body was giuen for vs, and his blood was ſhed for the redemption of our ſinnes:</hi> and ſecondly, becauſe the bread and the wine, which we take, eate, &amp; drinke according to Gods ordinance and inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, teacheth vs that by faith we take, eate, and drinke the body and blood of Ieſus Chriſt, as the onely foode and noriſhment of our ſoules.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſay you by all the faithleſſe and vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing members of mankind? can they eate the bodie of Ieſus Chriſt and drinke his blood?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>By no meanes: becauſe they want true faith, without the which we cannot be members of Chriſt, &amp; ſo conſequently ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not receiue any life of him who is the onely head of al the faithfull.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Then what benefite receiueth the Infidell if
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6460:24"/>
he communicate with the faithfull in this ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>He is ſo farre from receiuing an earneſt or pledge of his ſaluation,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> that <hi>he eateth and drinketh his owne damnation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>In what place is Ieſus Chriſt to be ſought for of the faithful, minding to lay hold on him, &amp; to poſſeſſe him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.</note>In heauen. <hi>For if we be riſen with Chriſt, we muſt ſeeke thoſe thinges which are aboue, where Christ ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at the right hand of God his Father.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Is not that the reaſon, why the Prieſts in old time, when they miniſtred the Supper, vſed to ſaie to the people: <hi>Surſum corda, Lift vp your hearts?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>It is the very true reaſon of that manner: and to the ſame purpoſe the people anſweared, <hi>Habemus ad Dominum, we lift them vp vnto the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Then how can we be coupled, or rather be made one with Ieſus Chriſt, who reſteth in the heauens, we remaining vpon the earth?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Child.</speaker>
                  <p>By Faith, and by the mightie working of the holie Ghoſt, to whom it is an eaſie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to knitte and to ioyne together whatſoeuer thinges be diuided and ſeuered by diſtance of place.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>What is your mind, or what ſhall we ſaie to thoſe that ſeeke Chriſt Ieſus in the elements of the Supper, namelie in the bread and the wine, affirming that the very ſubſtance of the bread &amp; wine is chainged into the ſubſtantiall bodie and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6460:24"/>
blood of Ieſus Chriſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Child.</speaker>
                  <p>We may boldlie affirme, that they are out of the way, for diuerſe cauſes. Firſt, in that directlie they gaineſay three ſeuerall Articles of our Faith, namelie, thoſe that import the <hi>aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſt vp into the heauens: his ſitting at the right hand of God: and his continuall abiding there vntill he come to iudge the quicke and the dead.</hi> And ſecondlie, by their vayne and ridiculous chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of ſubſtances, they aboliſh and take away the ſigne of the Sacrament, to wit, the breade and the wine, and ſo conſequentlie they take away the ſupper it ſelfe, which cannot remaine, if the ſigne thereof be taken awaie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Are not other groſſe &amp; vnreaſonable points to be founde, in this ſtraunge doctrine of their changing of ſubſtances?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>There are yet more: as theſe by name: that it giueth that which is holie to filthie ſwine, and no leſſe then the faithfull, maketh the Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del and vnbeleeuer partaker of this holie ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, wherein Ieſus Chriſt is giuen to be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and onelie of the faithfull: againe it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth men to become idolators, and to worſhip the Sacrament: alſo it maketh the glorious bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Ieſus Chriſt ſubiect to putrifying and to become no better then the filthie dung of mans bodie: and laſtlie it aboliſheth the true huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of the Sonne of God, becauſe it would haue his bodie to be infinite, and to be at once in all places.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Why? hath not Ieſus Chriſt witneſſed, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6460:25"/>
                     <hi>And lo, I am with you alway vntill the end of the world?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Actes</hi> 3.21.</note> &amp; againe, <hi>for where two or three are gathered together in my name, there am I in the midſt of them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>So it is: but theſe places import the preſence of his diuinitie, not the preſence of his humanity. And this I proue by the teſtimony of Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, who ſaith in the Goſpell: <hi>The poore ye ſhal haue alwaies with you, but me ye ſhal not haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies:</hi> alſo by that which S. Peter witneſſeth in the Actes, ſaying in theſe wordes concerning Chriſt, <hi>Whom the heauen must conteine, vntill the time that all things be reſtored.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Then you conclude, that Ieſus Chriſt, albeit he is among vs by his diuinitie &amp; his holy ſpirite, in reſpect of his humanity can be in no more then in one, &amp; that one a certaine place, and namelie in heauen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>That is my meaning, &amp; ſo ment S. Auguſtine ſaing, <hi>Till heauen &amp; earth ſhalbe deſtroyed, the Lord ſhal continually remaine aboue in the heauens.</hi> The Truth of the Lord alſo remaineth with vs: for it muſt needs be, that the body wherein he roſe vp, ſhould be in one, &amp; that a certaine place: but his Truth is ſpread ouer the face of the whole earth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>What is the ſum of this true faith, which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Ieſus Chriſt, not vpon the earth, but in the heauens?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 28. <hi>Math.</hi> 18.20</note>This is the ſumme: <hi>I beleeue in God the father,</hi> who hath created me: <hi>I beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> who hath redeemed me from ſinne, from Satan, from hel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; from death: <hi>I beleeue in the holie ghoſt,</hi> who ſanctifieth me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:6460:25"/>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſay you ſo in particular, I beleeue, and ſay not in generall, we beleeue?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe <hi>Euery man muſt examine himſelfe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Habac.</hi> 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.</note> 
                     <hi>and liue by his owne faith,</hi> not by the faith of other.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>And how may this be done?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>If we ſhal applie to euery of vs in particular, Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe with all his bleſſings and rich treaſures.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>What are the rich treaſures to be found in Ieſus Chriſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>There is ſaluation for them that are loſt, life for them that are dead, truth for them that are ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, wiſedome for them that are ignorant, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe for ſinners, holyneſſe and ſanctification for the vngodly, and redemption for captiues, &amp; them that are in bondage.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Muſt we not then by faith applie all thoſe things vnto our ſelues, ſeeing we are all by nature loſt, dead, lyars, ignorant, ſinful, defiled, vngodly, and captiues.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes verely. For Ieſus Chriſt hath taken vpon him al our neede &amp; miſerie, to make vs partakers of al his bleſſings &amp; rich treaſures which in verie deede, are diſtributed vnto vs in his holy Supper.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Now let vs ſpeake of the ſecond part of our dutie towards God, which conſiſteth in Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: and firſt, what is Repentance?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>It is a diſliking of that is euill, and a loue of that is good.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>To the end we may haue our ſins in diſliking &amp; hatred, is it not neceſſary, that we know them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>It is neceſſarie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:6460:26"/>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>How come we to haue knowledge of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill that dwelleth in vs?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohan</hi> 3.</note>Firſt we know by our original birth. For <hi>that which is borne of the fleſh, is fleſh.</hi> Secondly becauſe we tranſgreſſe the law of God, the rule of al per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and righteouſnes. And thirdly, by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary afflictions &amp; calamities that God ſendeth vpon vs for our ſinnes and iniquities.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>May we not alſo behold in the Sacraments a mirrour of our ſinnes and offences?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>We may. For if we were no ſinners we ſhold not ſtand in need of that forgiuenes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is ſignified in Baptiſme. And againe, except we were dead, it ſhould be in vaine that we come to the Supper to ſeek life &amp; ſaluation in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>When we know our ſinnes, are we there to reſt, and not to proceede further, namely to make confeſſion of the ſame?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31. <hi>&amp;</hi> 51. <hi>Luke</hi> 18.</note>We muſt alſo confeſſe our ſinnes after the example of Dauid and of the Publican, if we will obtaine righteouſneſſe before God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſhould it be neceſſarie for vs to know and to confeſſe our ſinnes before God?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>To the end we may obteine forgiuenes, and a ful and abſolute remiſſion, according as God is iuſt and faithfull to performe his promiſes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Why doth God forgiue vs our ſinnes?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.</note>To three eſpecial and principal ends &amp; pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes. Firſt that we ſhould be reconciled to our enemies: ſecondly, to the end we ſhould freelie forgiue them, &amp; thirdly, to the end we ſhould ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteine from ſinne and liue after righteouſneſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:6460:26"/>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Is there ought in the Supper which putteth vs in mind to flie from ſinne, and to abhor it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>There is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for euen the verie breaking of the bread in the Supper, doth teach vs that our ſinnes haue broken and bruſed the ſonne of God with the ſorrowes of death.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>What is hereupon to be gathered?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>That we ought to condemne our ſinnes and to haue them in abhomination, as the cauſes of the death of the ſonne of God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Is it ſufficient to abſteine from euil, without further proceeding in doing of good?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>No forſooth.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7</note> for <hi>Euery tree that bringeth not forth good fruit, is hewen downe, and caſt into the fire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And therefore is the euill and fooliſh ſeruant <hi>caſt into vtter darknes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 25.</note> not becauſe he had vnthriftilie ſpent his maſters talent, but becauſe by his dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and painefulneſſe he had done no good therewithall, ne had raiſed any commodity ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by vnto his maſter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Then be like it is requiſite that euery one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the talent which he hath receiued of God, ſhould glorifie him in that vocation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he is placed and appointed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Surely ſo it is, if we deſire to enter with the good ſeruant into the ioy of his maſter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>To the end we may do the thing that is good, ought we not to ſeeke the knowledge thereof?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>We ought: and namely by theſe meanes, by the law of God and generally by all the parts of the holy ſcripture, which teacheth vs plainelie what thoſe good workes are which God requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6460:27"/>
vs to performe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Whether doth the Supper, or any part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of exhort vs to a godly life, or no?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>It doth: for whereas we are vnited to Ieſus Chriſt, made fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bone: alſo, whereas we are made partakers of his holyneſſe and righteouſneſſe, we are taught that we ſhould be holy as he is holy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>What elſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Whereas we meete and aſſemble together in his holy Church, which is the communion of ſancts: wheras by the working of the holy ghoſt, we call vpon one father, who is moſt holy: laſtlie whereas we heare his holy and heauenly word, and alſo haue part of his holy ſacraments: we are exhorted, I ſay, by all theſe reaſons to an holines and pureneſſe of life.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Is this holineſſe, which God requireth of vs, perfect in this world or no?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>It is not: for ſo we vnderſtand euen by the examples of the ſancts themſelues during their life of mortality. And contrariwiſe, euen vntil the very laſt gaſpe, we ſhall continually haue neede to be humble ſuters to God for the remiſſion of our ſinnes in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Can this holineſſe being vnperfect be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and acceptable to God which is pefect?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea verily: ſo farre as we endeuour by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of his holy ſpirite &amp; by Faith, to obey the commandements of God, by Ieſus Chriſt, who with the cloke &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle of his own righteouſnes, couereth all our defalts, wants, &amp; imperfections.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:6460:27"/>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Now let vs come to the third point of our dutie towards God. Wherein ſaid you ere while it did conſiſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>In acknowledging the benefits we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued and daylie receiue of God, and chiefelie the benefite of our redemption by Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Is it not therefore, that the auncient fathers called the holy Supper, <hi>Euchariſtia,</hi> that is to ſay, a Thankeſgiuing?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>It is: and I ſay further, that this acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Gods benefites is neceſſary for all thoſe that communicate at the Lords table: as Ieſus Chriſt himſelf hath taught vs by his owne exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: &amp; hath commaunded vs beſide, to celebrate the Supper in remembrance of him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>How many conditions are to be regarded of vs in this acknowledging of Gods benefites?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>There are fower principall poynts: of which the firſt is, that this recogniſance is to be made to one God, by his only ſon Ieſus Chriſt: the ſecond, that it proceede not onely out of our mouthes, but alſo out of the verie bottome and ſecreat cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of our hearts.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Doth it not follow hereupon, that all thoſe that cal vpon ſancts, &amp; render not thanks to God alone by his ſon Ieſus Chriſt, are gretly deceiued?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes verily: &amp; on the other ſide, all hypocrites praying in an vnknowen &amp; ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guage, are no les out of the way, becauſe they honor &amp; worſhip God with their lips only, &amp; not with their hearts.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>What be the two other conditions annexed to this recogniſance, to the end it may be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:6460:28"/>
and agreeable to God our heauenly father?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>The one is, that it ought to be vſed at al times, to wit, as wel in aduerſitie as in proſperitie: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that it be practiſed priuatly &amp; alſo in publike &amp; in the midſt of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation of the faithful.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Now, ſeeing we haue ſufficiently ſpoken of our dutie towards God: let vs ſpeake of our duty towards our neighbour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſay, it conſiſteth in true loue &amp; brotherly v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, which of neceſſitie attendeth and waiteth vpon Faith and vpon the pure ſeruing and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>What is the true rule of loue and charitie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our neighbour?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>That we loue our neighbour as our ſelues: or that we loue one another, as Chriſt hath loued vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>How hath Ieſus Chriſt loued vs?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>He loued vs whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we were his enimies, wicked, vngracious &amp; abhominable in the ſight of God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Are not we taught by his example, to loue our enemies, though they be wicked and vngodlie perſons?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>We are: for in that point we muſt alſo be fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and faſhioned after the image of our head, Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Was the loue of Chriſt Ieſus, wherewith he loued vs, a feined loue, or hath it continued onely for a ſeaſon?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>No truely: for he hath loued vs, not onely in word, but alſo in deed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he hath not loued vs only for a ſhort time, but alſo euen to the end, to the death, and to the ſhedding of his precious blood
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6460:28"/>
for our ranſome.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>And ought we not herein to follow his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea that we ought, for the auoyding of all diſſembling and inconſtancie, ſo often as there is occaſion to loue our brethren, and to declare this our loue vnto them by our deeds.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Beſides the example of Ieſus Chriſt, are we not exhorted to this true loue, by certeine reaſons and arguments in the Supper?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>We are: and firſt in that we communicate all together in one companie, that we eate the ſame meate, that we call vpon the ſame father, that we haue all of vs one head Ieſus Chriſt, that we are al quickned by his holy ſpirit, in theſe reſpects I ſay, we ought to be ſtirred vp to true loue &amp; brotherly Charitie one towards another. Secondly the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the bread &amp; the wine which we receiue in the ſupper, ought to exhort vs to the ſame charity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe, that, euen as the bread is made of many cornes, which afterward are ioyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the making of one loafe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the wine is made of many grapes, which afterwards are preſſed together to the making of one liquour: ſo ought al the profeſſors of Chriſt, which are many being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered ſingle &amp; ſeueral, to be made one by loue in one body, which is the church of God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Can this loue whereunto we are exhorted in the Supper by ſo many reaſons, abide and dwell in them whoſe hearts are full of hatred and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice towards their brethren?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:6460:29"/>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>It cannot: &amp; therfore we muſt put all wrongs and iniuries out of our minds, we muſt be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to thoſe with whom we haue bin offended, we muſt forgiue and pardon them freely, euen ſo as we pray vnto God that he would forgiue and pardon vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>Then we may wel conclude vpon the whole that hath bin hitherto ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that all thoſe, which do not their duty as wel towards God as towards their neighbour, ought not to be admitted to the holy Supper.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>We may indeed and therefore the true mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Chriſt, ought to be very circumſpect &amp; wel aduiſed, that he <hi>Giue not that which is holy to thoſe that are</hi> commonly knowen, &amp; as it were pointed at of al men with the finger, for <hi>Dogs and ſwine.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F.</speaker>
                  <p>The God of al mercy &amp; loue ſo garniſh &amp; fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh our hearts with faith, &amp; repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance, that with a pure &amp; ſyncere affection we may both publiſh &amp; ſhew forth his praiſes, and alſo loue our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors as Ieſus Chriſt hath loued vs, to the end we come not to his holy table as infidels and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent wretches do, to our owne damnation, but rather to our euerlaſting ſaluation: being well aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured and certeinly perſwaded, that ſo truely we ſhal enioy the life, the benefits, and the rich trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours of Ieſus Chriſt, as we vſe the elements which he hath appointed &amp; ordeined to be moſt certeyne and vnfallible tokens of life euerlaſting, in the ſame his welbeloued Sonne our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:6460:29"/>
            <head>A DIALOGVE EN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TREATING OF THE LORD HIS SVPPER. <hi>Made by I. de l'Espine, Minister of the word of God.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Miniſter.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou know my brethren, that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt when hee inſtituted his holie ſupper commaunded vs to prooue our ſelues before we doe eate of the breade and drinke of the cuppe which are offered vnto vs therein; threatning and fearing vs with our own condemnation if we preſume contrarie to his commandement to eate and to drinke not diſcerning the Lord his bodie. And foraſmuch as by reaſon of my duetie, I haue to accompt before his maieſtie, not onelie for my ſelfe, but alſo for you which haue beene com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to my charge: I purpoſe to examine you all one after another, touching this point, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I do admit you, or any of you to this holie table: that I may vnderſtand whether you haue ſufficient inſtruction in theſe matters, and haue rightlie conceiued and kept in memorie ſuch
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6460:30"/>
points as I haue of late times handled for your better preparing thereunto. Wherefore I praie you <hi>Euſebius</hi> anſwere me, and tell me what is the chiefeſt thing and moſt requiſite to be knowen for the ſufficient vnderſtanding of this whole myſterie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>The chiefeſt point wherein you ſaid wee ought to be perfectlie informed and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, was to my vnderſtanding and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, touching the Author, by whom the Supper was ordeined: and that it was not to be taken for ſome dreame, or thing onelie imagined &amp; conceiued in the braine &amp; fancie of man, but for an holie &amp; an inuiolable ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of our God; which, without great impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; preiudice to our owne ſaluation, we can neither breake in the whole, nor neglect in any part or parcell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>What was my reaſon for this firſt and principall point?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>It was to this effect, that except we haue a certeine knowledge and aſſurance, that this ceremonie is one of God his owne ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, we cannot be perſwaded in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, that in keeping the ſame we do pleaſe his maieſtie: and further, that except this point haue taken deepe roote in our hearts by the power of his worde, we are prone and readie continuallie to take away the honor and eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation thereunto belonging: and by reputing it either a vaine and needeleſſe matter, or at the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6460:30"/>
moſt a thing indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to be receiued or refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, we are euer at the point to ſet light by it &amp; to deride it: For euen therefore deſpiſe we the whole rable of Turkiſh &amp; Iewiſh ceremonies, becauſe they are grounded onely vpon the wil of ſuch as ordeined them, and vpon the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious ignorance and blindneſſe of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people which keepe and worſhip them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>Shew me now by whom it was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed: to the end we may vnderſtand what we do, when we come to the Lord his table. For as you haue verie well ſaid, it is not onelie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for the aſſuring &amp; ſtaying of our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences that our faith be builded vpon his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, but alſo that our obedience be ſquared &amp; ruled by his commandements: to the end that our inward intention &amp; meaning in all things may be guided and gouerned by the light of his word: and as we do acknowledge him to be our father by the truſt that we repoſe vpon his goodneſſe, ſo we may in like manner con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe him to be our ſouereigne Lorde, by the feare and reuerence which we ſhall carrie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his heauenlie maieſtie, &amp; by the careful minds which we ſhal ſhew to be in vs towards the keeping of his ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces: proteſting here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by that we will hope to receiue nothing but at his hands, and that we will commit nothing which ſhall not be agreeable to his holie will and pleaſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>This holie ſupper was ordeined and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6460:31"/>
appointed by our Lord &amp; maſter Ieſus Chriſt, as it appeareth by that which is written by his holy Euangeliſts,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. <hi>Mark.</hi> 14. <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> ſainct Mathew, Marke, and Luke, in their ſeueral writings, and by his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle S. Paul in his firſt to the Corinthians: in which places after he had diſtributed the bread and wine to his diſciples he commanded them to do the like in the remembrance of him, and thereby to declare his death, and to preach the ſame vntill his comming.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>Then it is out of all doubt that the ſupper is a ceremonie ordeined and appointed by God, and that all the faithfull thereof cape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, are bounde to celebrate the ſame by his commandement. But foraſmuch as that due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ought to be moſt reuerently performed, and for the better and more holie vſe thereof it is needefull to vnderſtand to what end and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it was ordeined, I would haue you to ſhew me for the ſecond point, what is the end of the Lord his ſupper.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>The ſupper was inſtituted to this end and purpoſe, that we might thereby be edified and inſtructed, which thing Ieſus Chriſt did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſet as a marke before his eyes in all that he either taught or appointed to be done in his Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Minist.</speaker>
               <p>How and wherein are we taught &amp; edified by celebrating the ſupper?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>We are inſtructed in Faith and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, the onely points wherein the ſaluation &amp;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6460:31"/>
dutie of al Chriſtians, and in general the whole body of the religion of our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt is conteined.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>How I pray you is our faith hereby edified?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>Our faith is edified,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> as the Apoſtle ſaith, when we are inſtructed, comforted, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted, and aſſured by the worde of God, and when as by his ſpirite the power thereof is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauen in our hearts. Nowe both the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that is to wit, of Baptiſme and of the Lord his Supper, are nothing elſe (as it is nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſaid of Sainct Auguſtine) but viſible words, wherein, as it were in goodly and faire Tables, God ſetteth out before our eyes, his loue, his fauour, his benefits and graces drawen in liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and naturall colours: to the end that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the ſame therein, and ſetting our eies firmelie vpon the gratious goodneſſe that hee ſheweth to vs therein expreſſed, might be well aſſured and comforted in our conſciences &amp; be euen ſo affected, as we are when we doe either reade the gratious letters or behold the liuelie pictures of our louing friends.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>What be thoſe graces and benefits which we are principallie to conſider in the Supper?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>That Ieſus Chriſt, who is there repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, is our life; that is the heauenlie breade ſent downe from his father vpon the earth for the nouriſhment &amp; ſuſtentation of our ſoules:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6460:32"/>
that in taking the bread and wine, we are recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into the communion of his bodie, and ſo conſequently, aſſured to be partakers of his righteouſneſſe and obedience, which are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to all them that are knit together and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited in one with him: further, that he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed vs, and made eternall ſatiſfaction for al our ſinnes: that he hath purged and cleanſed our filthie ſpots and blemiſhes with his blood: that the ſentence of condemnation pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt him, is our abſolution: that the paiment, which he hath made, is a full and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect acquittance and warrant for all our debts: that he is the ſacrifice, by the which the wrath of God againſt vs hath beene appeaſed and pacified: and that his death is the meane, whereby we are reconciled to him, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into his fauour; without the which we can hope neither for life nor ſaluation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay, <hi>Euſebius,</hi> that the principal point, that is taught vs in the myſterie of the ſupper, and that we are to learne therein and to cal to remembrance ſo often as we come to the table to celebrate the ſame, is that Ieſus Chriſt is our life: neuertheleſſe it ſeemeth that this is contrarie to that which you lately ſaide, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the fruites of Faith and attributing thereunto our ſaluation: and further repugnant to that which is written in the Pſalmes, where Dauid magnifying the graces of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.</note> ſaieth, That in him is the wel of life; and that our light
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6460:32"/>
proceedeth onelie from his brightnes. Fo if the humanitie of Ieſus Chriſt crucified and offered vp vnto God for our redemption, is the cauſe of our life, how can it be that God &amp; our Faith are the cauſes and occaſions thereof?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>The one of theſe is no hinderance to the other, as you declared vnto vs at large in one of your ſermons. It is moſt certeine, and of al men confeſſed, that God is the author of our life: and that in him we haue our being, feeling, mouing, and vnderſtanding. Further, that in beholding his ſhining countenance, conſiſteth the full contentment of all our deſires, and our moſt perfect and bleſſed eſtate: becauſe it is the chiefeſt &amp; moſt ſouereigne good, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending vnder it all other particular good things, hath ſufficient in that reſpect to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and ſatiſfie all our appetites and deſires, when we haue obteined &amp; do enioie the ſame. But the meane to haue fruition and poſſeſſion thereof, and to drawe neere vnto him, is Ieſus Chriſt his ſon. For euen as without God there is no life; ſo without Ieſus Chriſt there is no God, as S. Iohn doth witneſſe, ſayeng:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh</hi> 2.</note> whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer denieth the Sonne, the ſame hath not the Father: and, whoſoeuer confeſſeth the Sonne, the ſame hath the Father alſo. And Sainct Paul in his Epiſtles written to the Galathians and Epheſians; to whom hee ſheweth that in the time of their ignorance, and when they knewe not Ieſus Chriſt, they were without
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6460:33"/>
God in the world. And this is the cauſe why he was called by the Angel and by the Prophet, Emanuel, which in Hebrewe is as much to ſay, as, God is with vs: to ſhew vnto vs that there is no other meane to ioyne and knit vs together with him, then that meane of his ſonne; which may alſo be prooued by this reaſon. It is not poſſible for vs to haue anie fellowſhippe with God, who is righteous and a moſt cleare and perfect light, ſo long as wee continue in our ſinnes and darkneſſe: in as much as two things ſo fully and directlie contrarie, cannot meete together, ne endure ech other. Wherefore it muſt needes be that before any agreement or league can be entreated of betwene him &amp; vs, we are to be freed &amp; deliucred from the cauſes of our ſeparation from God, which can by no other meane be compaſſed and obtained then by Ieſus Chriſt. For he is the true light which enlighteneth euerie man th<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> commeth into the world:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ihon</hi> 1.</note> he is the Lamb that taketh awaie our ſinnes. Whereupon it foloweth of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that if we wil be reconciled and ioyned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, wee muſt bee made partakers of the righteouſneſſe of his ſonne and muſt be ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened by his ſpirit: to the end that he couering our filthyneſſe &amp; imperfections with the one, and driuing away by litle and litle the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that dwelleth in vs with the other, may hereby take away the lettes and hinderances, by the which this happie league and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6460:33"/>
is broken and turned aſide from our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifite. And foraſmuch as he is the way by the which we are to come to this agreement, and ſo conſequently to the life and felicitie that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth thereon. For this cauſe he is called life as well as his Father.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6.</note> Whoſoeuer eateth my fleſh (ſaith he) &amp; drincketh my blood, hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life: for my fleſh is meate in deed, &amp; my blood is drinke in deed. He that eateth my fleſh and drinketh my blood, dwelleth in me, and I in him. As the liuing Father hath ſent me, ſo liue I by the Father: and he that eateth me, euen he ſhal liue by me. Al which places do ſerue to no other end &amp; purpoſe, then to giue vs to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that his humanitie, crucified for our ſinnes hath the power to bring vs to life, &amp; to quicken vs, by reconciling vs vnto God, when we eate thereof: that is to ſaie, when we by a true and liuelie Faith do, as it were, get a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety in the ſa<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e vnto our ſelues, and being v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited &amp; ingrafted into it, do lie there as it were at a ſure anker, by a firme and ſtedfaſt truſt and confidence. For by this meane we are ioyned vnto the diuinitie, which is the wel of life &amp; of al bleſſedneſſe. For this cauſe Tertullian ſaieth that our fleſh is fedde with the fleſh of Ieſus Chriſt, to the end that our ſoule maie be refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed &amp; filled with God. To which purpoſe we may refer two notable places of S. Auguſtine, the one in his commentaries vppon S. lohn: where he ſaieth (ſpeaking of the faithful man)
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6460:34"/>
By Chriſt thou commeſt to Chriſt: by Chriſt man, to Chriſt God. By the word which was made fleſh, to the worde which was in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning with GOD: by the breade which is eaten of men, to that which is eaten of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. The other place is in one of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies vppon the Pſalmes, where he ſetteth foorth a moſt excellent compariſon taken from the Nource and her young childe. The nource and the childe (ſaieth hee) doe eate one ſelfe and the ſame meate, but after a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe manner: for the milke which the childe ſucketh out of her breſtes, is the breade that his nource before had eaten: but for the better preparing and ordering of it in ſuch ſort as the childe might let it downe, and thereby receiue his nouriſhment, it was needefull that firſt i<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould be incarnate in her, and that it ſhould be tourned into blood in her lyuer, to the ende it might become the more ſweete and delicate for the childe his drinking, and being carried from the lyuer to the breſts, that it ſhoulde be there chaunged into milke, and euen there ſhould receiue a ſtraunge kinde of whiteneſſe, leaſt the childe ſeeing it in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer colour ſhould haue beene afraide of it and abhorre it. Euen ſo (ſaith he) ſoone after ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying his compariſon, the Angels and we do liue and are fedde with one and the ſame foode: for neither they nor we haue anie ſtrength or life, or liuelineſſe, but by the onelie euerlaſting
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6460:34"/>
and almightie worde of God: neither is there anie other difference, but that the foode that they receiue in meate, wee receiue in milke: for by reaſon of our infirmitie and weakeneſſe, it was needefull that this word ſhould be made fleſh, and by that meane ſhould be applied to the capacity and ſtrength of our ſtomacke, that we might be able to digeſt it, and to be nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and ſuſteined by it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſter.</speaker>
               <p>I perceiue <hi>Euſebius,</hi> that you were not in ſleepe at my ſermon, who doe ſo faithfullie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe what you haue heard. O that it might pleaſe God that all the reſt of my auditours woulde bee ſo attentiue and had ſo great and ſingular deſire to make profite by the worde, as I verilie beleeue you haue. But the further I proceede in my excerciſe, I haue the better ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that for the moſt part they are ſo cold and careleſſe, that I am conſtrained to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of them, and to ſhew you my griefe in that behalfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſebius.</speaker>
               <p>If I be diligent to learne the worde of God, and in anie ſmall meaſure capable of the knowledge thereof, I am bounde to render vnto him all praiſe and thankes, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that without his Spirite of my owne nature I ſhoulde haue as litle taſte and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thereof, as the moſt carnall and earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie manne in the worlde. But to the ende
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6460:35"/>
we do not diſcontinue and breake off our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer matter, if memorie faile not, for a further and more full declaration of the myſterie whereof we do now intreate, to the former ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of ſainct Auguſtine you ioyned ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taken from the bodie of man, the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers whereof cannot by any meanes haue part of the life which ſpringeth &amp; proceedeth from the ſoule remaining in the bodie, except they be vnited and ioyned with it: no more is it poſſible for vs to be quickened by this fulneſſe of the Godheade which (as ſainct Paul ſaieth) dwelleth bodily in Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.</note> and giueth life to the whole Church, except we be members of his bodie, fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſter.</speaker>
               <p>You haue ſufficientlie declared how the humanitie and fleſh of Ieſus Chriſt is the meane of our life. But as concerning Faith, whereof the Prophet and Apoſtle haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Abac.</hi> 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.</note> that the iuſt ſhall liue by it, how are we to vnderſtand this point?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>I ſaid at the firſt that there is no life without God, and next, that there is no God without Ieſus Chriſt: nowe I ſaie following the like courſe, that there is no Ieſus Chriſt without Faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for by Faith we rcceiue him, as Sainct Iohn witneſſeth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.</note> and he commeth to dwell in our hearts, as Sainct Paul writeth to the Epheſians,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.</note> by Faith: which he confirmeth by his owne mouth, ſaying. If anie man loue
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6460:35"/>
me he wil keepe my word, and my Father will loue him, and we will come vnto him, and will dwell with him. For the vnion which we haue with him is ſpirituall and like to that which is betweene the husbande and the wife. For e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as they be ioyned and coupled together for euer by mutuall promiſes and by that faith and truth wherin thoſe promiſes are mutuallie accepted, notwithſtanding that their bodies do change neither the outward ſhape &amp; forme, ne yet their natural kind and ſexe; and that for this coupling and knitting of man and wife it is not required or meant that both of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhold viſibly become one body, like as wine and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter being mingled together in one cuppe or veſſel: ſo to marrie and to ioyne vs to Ieſus Chriſt, it is not needeful that our bodies ſhold be bound in one with his bodie, as we ſee the members of one bodie are bound together by the muſcles, cordes, ſinewes and griſtles of the ſame: which happening it would be the moſt monſtrous thing that a man could ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine to be in nature. But the chiefe and onelie matter is, that thoſe promiſes which he maketh vnto vs, namely, to comfort vs, if we wil come vnto him, to defend vs, to ſaue, to quicken vs, to redeeme vs, to raiſe vs vp from the dead, to pardon vs, and ſuch like, that his promiſes (I ſaie) be beleeued of vs and firmelie perſwaded, that wee like and accept of them, and haue aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance in them, promiſinge vnto him in like
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6460:36"/>
manner on our behalfes, that we acknowledge none other then him alone for our King and Prieſt, our ſheppard and our Prophet: that we wil heare no other voice or doctrine but his: that for our ſatiſfaction, remiſſion, and ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we wil vſe no other ſacrifice the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that, which is once offered for vs: that we wil chuſe none other Aduocate or Attornie then him, when we would be recommended in anie of our ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities to the good grace and fauor and ayde of his Father: that for our defence and ſafegard againſt the euil ſpirit and againſt al other our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies we wil haue recourſe, and put our whol affiance in his powre and ſtrength: and to be breife, that we wil not hold our life and our whole felicitie of any other then of him. In theſe promiſes giuen, taken, and kept of both parties, conſiſteth the alliance and league, that we haue with Ieſus Chriſt. And euen as a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that is lawfullie married to an husband miſdoubteth not, albeit her huſband abide at Conſtantinople and ſhe at Paris, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſundring of their bodies, and greate diſtance betweene the places, where they abide, they are neuertheleſſe one fleſh, and that there is a perfect coniunction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, and ſuch a bonde and knot of friendſhip as is not to be looſed: ſo albeit that Chriſt Ieſus be in heauen and we vpon the earth, we ought certeinely to be perſwaded that after the marriage made betweene him
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6460:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and vs by the meane of Faith, wherein we haue accepted his foreſaide promiſes, we are one with him, and that this vnion is nothing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached by the difference of places, where we abide and continue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>Then your meaning is, that Faith is not the cauſe of our life, but inaſmuch as it doth marrie vs to Ieſus Chriſt, by whom we are afterwarde ledde and conducted euen to God, with whom we finde all the happineſſe that we can aske and deſire. This is verie well meant and vnderſtoode of you: But what will you ſay to that which Sainct Paul hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten touching the word of the Goſpel,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.</note> that it is the power of God vnto ſaluation to all belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>Sainct Paul ſaieth ſo, becauſe there is no Faith without the worde, no more then there is Ieſus Chriſt without Faith:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.</note> for Faith commeth by hearing, &amp; hearing by the word of God. And to this purpoſe is the preaching of the Goſpel, and the adminiſtration of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments. By the one the Spirite of God inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth and planteth Faith in our hearts, &amp; by the other he confirmeth and eſtabliſheth the ſame: to the end that by this meane being made the members of Ieſus Chriſt, we might draw nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer vnto God, and liue in him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>Then the ſum of al that you haue hitherto diſcourſed is, that our bleſſed eſtate &amp; eternal life, is to poſſeſſe God; and to poſſeſſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6460:37"/>
him, to be members of Ieſus Chriſt: and to be his members, to haue Faith; and to haue Faith, that the Goſpell be preached and the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments adminiſtred vnto vs: in as much as Faith is engendred by the word, and after confirmed nouriſhed, and encreaſed in vs, by the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thereunto annexed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>You propounded vnto vs a ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the lampe which ſeemed vnto me a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie fitte and proper waie to declare vnto vs in ſome good manner, the properties and vſe as well of Faith, as of the Sacraments: you ſaid that Faith was like vnto the fire, in as much as by the light thereof it bringeth vs to the ſight and knowledge of God, of Ieſus Chriſt our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing health, and of our ſelues: that the cotton, about the which the fire is lighted, did reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the word &amp; the gracious promiſes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſaid Faith is built and founded: and that the ſacraments are as the oyle, that ſerueth to keepe in the fire, ſo as it neither be diminiſhed, nor put out altogether.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>Can you remeber the matter, which I drew out of this ſimilitude, &amp; the end where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I brought it into my diſcourſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>I take it that it was to ſhew vnto vs, that the Supper can ſerue vs to ſmall purpoſe, vnleſſe that firſt we be furniſhed with Faith in our hearts, &amp; that is it of no more vſe then oyle is in a lampe when no fire is lighted, or then a ſeale to a letter wherein is nothing written.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:6460:37"/>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>Then you may perceaue, <hi>Euſebius,</hi> and vnderſtande, that it is not without great reaſon that the ancient fathers haue called theſe two ceremonies of Baptiſme, and of the Supper, myſteries and ſacraments, the deepe, diuine, and hidden ſenſe and meaning of them conſidered: and that S. Auguſtine hath not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe applied that vnto them, which is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of God by Dauid in the Pſalmes:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.</note> that <hi>He made darkeneſſe his ſecret place, and his pauilion round about him, euen darkeneſſe of waters, ana cloudes of the ayre.</hi> For who woulde thinke at the firſt aſſaie, that the gracious fauour of God, the benefite of Ieſus Chriſt, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of ſinnes, and generally all the partes of our ſaluation, and redemption, were ſo excellentlie ſet out in a little water, breade and wine, as you haue <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eclared vnto vs in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularitie? Dauid called the ancient ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies &amp; the order that was kept in the Church in his daies, <hi>The face of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.</note> becauſe the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full did therin ſee and behold, as in a glaſſe, his promiſes, his fauour, and his gracious good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But this name may be more properlie giuen to our ceremonies, becauſe they are more ſignificant, and doe beare the markes and tokens of his fauour towardes vs, more liuelie and perfectlie ſet out, and more deepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie imprinted in them, then the other. But I ſuppoſe you haue nowe ſufficientlie declared how our faith is edified by the Sacramentes:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6460:38"/>
proceede to the reſt, and ſhewe me by what meane our charitie is inſtructed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.</note>Sainct Paul ſaieth, that <hi>we that are manie are one breade, and one bodie, becauſe we all are partakers of one bread.</hi> Euen as therefore in the ſupper we are taught that there is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meane to obtaine ſaluation then by Ieſus Chriſt, deade and crucified for vs: ſo wee doe proteſt by the bread and wine that we receiue, that, if we wil be partakers of this ſaluation, we muſt be vnited and made one with him, and in him al of vs together one with another. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto is required a charitie, not of the tongue, the outward geſture or ſpeach, not common or ordinarie, not cold and remiſſe: but an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and heartie affection, holding vs alſo faſt, and locking vs, at it were, ſo ſure and ſo cloſe together in one bodie, that if it were a thing poſſible a man might no ſooner ſunder &amp; deuide vs one from an other, then the grains of corne after the bread is baken, or the grapes can be deuided when the wine is tunned.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, but can it be that when wee come to the table we ſhould ſo perfectlie loue each other, as that there be not in the whole body of the Church more then one heart, one ſoule, one ſpirite, and one minde?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>In this caſe we doe not ſpeake of that Faith and Charitie, which we haue, or can haue when we celebrate the ſupper: but of that onely which is taught vs therin: for I haue
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6460:38"/>
heard you ſay, and rehearſe often, that their is great difference betwene the power of man, and the duetie of man, betweene his practiſe, and his precepts, and that we are alwaies more indebted then we vſe to pay, euen as we are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer better taught and inſtructed, then we can learne or followe. For the wiſdome of God being perfect and infinite, it cannot be but the law (as Dauid ſaieth) proceeding from him,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.</note> muſt needs be verie entire and perfect. But if our power and habilitie to keepe the lawe be either none at all, or ſo weake, as it can verie hardlie ſtirre ad remooue it ſelfe: how is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that our obedience ſhould not be vnper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect? in like manner our faith, our charitie, and in generall whatſoeuer we doe, or whatſoeuer proceedeth from vs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>You ſaie well, <hi>Euſebius,</hi> we maie not confound or trouble the order that is to be kept in handling of this matter: and it ſuffiſeth that you haue now ſhewed vs what is taught and ſignified vnto vs in the Supper: for you ſhall more fitlie and more conuenientlie ſhew forth the propertie of Faith &amp; Charitie which we are to bring with vs to this Supper, when we ſhall entreate what courſe and meane we ought to follow, to come vnto it worthilie. Now to continue the veine of your diſcourſe, you ſhall giue vs to vnderſtande, who they be that are inuited and bidden to this ſupper, and whither that all manner of perſons indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6460:39"/>
are fit to celebrate the ſame?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>As they did eate</hi> (ſaith S. Mathew) <hi>Ieſus tooke the breade, and after hee had giuen thankes, hee brake it, and gaue it to his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</hi> He noteth plainely, that the bread which he did take and breake in the ſupper was giuen onelie to his diſciples and ſcholers, to ſignifie vnto vs, that we doe eate it vnworthilie, if we know not Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; be not in ſome good meaſure inſtructed in his goſpel. And ſo by this reaſon are excluded &amp; barred from this feaſt al ignorant perſons, all Infidels, contemners, and blaſphemers. For if the Sacrament was not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined to any other purpoſe, as was ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, then for the confirming, exerciſing, and increaſing of our faith: what benefite would it be vnto vs if there were no faith to be found in our heartes? Furthermore, is the end whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it was deputed, be to ſhadow foorth and to ſet before our eyes Ieſus Chriſt crucified, how can this end be attained and compaſſed, if our eyes be out and we remaine in blindenes? For the light is for none other then for ſuch as haue eyes to ſee it. Againe if we be dead, as in truth we are no better being vtterly voide of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and beleife, the breade that is ordeined onely to ſhape and to ſtrengthen the life of him that eateth, cannot be profitable vnto vs, except we be firſt reuiued and raiſed vp againe from death. And yet further, for what reaſon willeth S. Paul,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> that we ſhould <hi>Examine
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6460:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and prooue our ſelues before wee come to the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> But onelie to geue vs knowledge, that we are vtterlie vnworthie of that benefite, being vnfurniſhed of Faith, which is ſo neceſſarie for the good and lawful vſe therof? for if al thinges be polluted and defiled to the vnbeleeuers, yea if our daylie &amp; ordinarie meates are not ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied but by the word and by praier: if whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is done without Faith, be ſinne: howe ſhould not this holie miſterie be prophaned and made vnholie, when we, either plainelie ignorant, or not ſufficientlie taught, are ſo har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die as to ſet vs downe at the king his table, and to goe to the mariage of his ſonne without our wedding garment? Further why is it that Ieſus Chriſt ſo ſtraightlie forbiddeth his Apoſtles, <hi>To giue that which is holy vnto doggs, and to caſt pearles before ſwine,</hi> but onlie to admoniſh them that they become wiſe, and well aduiſed to diſpenſe the word &amp; the miſteries of God? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, the commandement of God, wherin we are charged, that <hi>We take not his name in vaine,</hi> is plainly &amp; generally giuen to al men: neither yet may we ſuppoſe, as you did teach vs verie well, that onely falſe oathes are in that commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t forbidden: for euery vnlawful vſing as wel of his name, as of his word, and of his ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces is in like manner therin contained. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it remaineth that we conclude vpon the former reaſons, that the faithful onlie are cape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to celebrate the Lord his Supper. And by
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6460:40"/>
the faithfull I do vnderſtand thoſe that haue a liuelie and actuall faith, begotten of the word of God, and grounded vpon his promiſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>I take great pleaſure and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in you, <hi>Euſebius,</hi> in that you are ſo dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent &amp; paineful to gather ſuch textes and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as are alleaged to prooue &amp; to perſwade that which a man ſhall vndertake. For it is not poſſible that by anie other meane the faith of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie man in the world could be faſt, &amp; firme, and well aſſured, and that he could render a reaſon of his beliefe, to thoſe that require him to make an accompt thereof: which thing is eaſilie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimented in diuers, that haue ſome know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge &amp; opinion of the trueth; but becauſe the ſame is not wel grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded nor fenſed with ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it cannot be ſound and perfect, ne yet of anie great edifying, which I thought good to touch beſide the matter, whereof we do princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pallie entreat, to the end that hereafter you be yet more curious to follow the ſame courſe &amp; cuſtome. And now to come again to our chiefe matter; hauing ſhewed what is the myſterie of the ſupper, and who they be that God biddeth to the ſame; it is time that you proceede and go forward, and that you tell vs how we ought to draw neere, and to preſent our ſelues vnto it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note>The Apoſtle ſaieth: <hi>Let euerie man examine himſelfe, and ſo let him eate of that bread, and drinke of that cuppe.</hi> Wherein he warneth vs diligentlie to examin our conſciences, ſo often
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6460:40"/>
as we are minded &amp; purpoſed to celebrate the ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>Wherein ought we to examin our ſelues?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>In two points: to wit, whither we haue both Faith and Charitie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>What maner of Faith is required?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>The whole Chriſtian Faith is in a ſum conteined in the Apoſtles Creed: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are to conſider, not onely whither we do vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the hiſtory of thoſe things, which are briefelie ſet forth therin by articles; as, That Ieſus Chriſt hath taken our nature, that he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, roſe again, &amp; aſcended into heauen, where he ſitteth at the right hande of his Father, and from thence he ſhall come to iudge both the quicke and the dead: but it is further requiſite, that we ſearch and ſound the bottome of our hearts, to know whither they be ſetled and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed vpon that which we confeſſe, as vpon the onely meane of our ſaluation, and whither we be reſolued to perſeuer and continue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantlie in this affiance and truſt onelie, euen to the ende of our naturall life, renouncing all other as moſt vaine and pernitious to our ſaluation. And aboue all things wee ought to beware that we be not deceiued by hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie or ſimplicitie, which may bring vs in a conceipt, that a bare opinion and credulitie or lightneſſe of beliefe, is true Faith: for there is nothing that can make ſo greeuous a fault ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6460:41"/>
but rather it is damnable before the maieſtie of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Minist.</speaker>
               <p>Whereby may we learne and iudge that we haue a true and ſyncere faith, and ſuch a Faith as is required to the worthie eating of the breade at the Lord his table?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>When we do perfectlie vnderſtand the things that are deliuered in the articles of the Apoſtles Creed, with the end of Chriſt his comming into the world: when we are well and ſurelie perſwaded of the truth and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teintie of them, and this perſwaſion doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and aſſure our conſciences of the remiſſion of our ſinnes, in ſuch manner as it taketh awaie the horror and the dreadfull conceipt that we haue apprehended of God his eternall iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Laſtlie, when this is ſo deepely engrauen and imprinted in our hearts, that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding anie temptation or affliction that may happen vnto vs, we do alwaies holde a ſtedfaſt hope of his gratious fauor, &amp; of the life eternall that dependeth vpon the ſame: then we may aſſure our ſelues that we haue a Chriſtian Faith allowed and approoued of him, in the vſe and receiuing or vnderſtanding of his myſteries.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>And would you require in a man perfect knowledge of the Creed, in the which the whole ſum of the ſcriptures is in a manner conteined? and further, perfect truſt and affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in all the promiſes of God, the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment and fulfilling of the which is procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6460:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
vnto vs by the interceſſion and fauour of his ſonne? and thirdlie a conſtancie in all this ſo perfect, that no temptation ſhould ſhake vs and make vs to ſtagger therein, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe exclude it and caſt it out from the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>No: for the Apoſtles themſelues, to whom Ieſus Chriſt did firſt diſtribute the ſame, were vnperfect in all this matter, as experience ſhewed in the temptation that happened vnto them ſoone after. Further, if we ſhould not be fit to receiue it except our Faith were fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; then it is euident it ſhould haue beene in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted and ordeined in vaine, for ſo long as we continue in this mortal life, we are no more able to beleeue in God perfectlie, then we are able to know or to loue him perfectlie. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, the end for which it was ordeined, is it not to vphold and to vnderſet our Faith? If then our Faith had beene ſufficientlie ſtrong and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of it ſelfe, what vſe ſhould there be of the ſacraments? Theſe reaſons are ſufficient to prooue, that we are not vncapeable of the Lord his ſupper, by the imperfection and weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our Faith: prouided allwaies, that the ſame be vnfeined, and that we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging the baſeneſſe and weakeneſſe thereof, do praie vnto God to haue it augmented and increaſed by the working of his holie Spirite: and alſo that to this end we vſe the meanes that he hath left to be vſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:6460:42"/>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>It is ſufficient that we beleeue that Ieſus Chriſt by his obedience hath purchaſed vnto vs the grace of God, and in this grace and fauour hath gotten vs righteouſneſſe and life: and that by his croſſe, he making ſatiſfaction for our ſinnes hath appeaſed his wrath, and hath freed vs from the danger of death, and of the curſſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>No ſyr; but when we haue beleeued thus much, we muſt be well aſſured that we are receiued into the communion of this obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence &amp; ſatiſfaction, when we receiue the bread and the wine which are preſented vnto vs in the ſupper. And for the laſt and moſt principall point, we muſt beleeue that we are made one, and incorporate with Ieſus Chriſt, and allowed of him &amp; of his Father, not onely for his flocke, his diſciples, his brethren and friends, but alſo for members of his bodie, and fleſh of his fleſh. Out of which point we may drawe matter of ſingular and manifold comforts and conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. For by this meane we are ſure, that ſo long as we continue in this vnion, we cannot be condemned ne kept &amp; holden in the bands of death, no more then he himſelfe: and that the prince of this world hath no more part in vs, or power ouer vs, then he hath in or ouer him: and that righteouſnes and life are as well inſeparable from vs, as from him: and that we are coheires with him of all the honor of his kingdome: &amp; that where he is, there we ſhalbe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6460:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of neceſſitie, not impeacheable by al the power and practiſes of the Deuill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>I haue two queſtions to aſke you, touching that you ſaid euen now of the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation, that we haue in the humanitie of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, when we do take and eate the bread in the ſupper. The firſt is, whither that before the bread is giuen vnto vs, we be not already v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited vnto him; and if we be, what profit we can receaue by the ſupper?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>It is neceſſarie that by Faith we be ioyned vnto him, before we come vnto the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: otherwiſe we ſhould be wholie vnworthy: and yet we come, that we maie be yet more neerelie knit in one with him. For euen as two diuers things, when they be tyed &amp; bound to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with a corde, maie be yet tied with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and if a man would vſe an hundred cordes to that purpoſe, it might be verie well ſaied, that they are ſtill tied together more and more: ſo albeit that we by baptiſme and Faith, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we heare and obey the word of God, are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied vnto him, and ingrafted in the bodie of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, yet that is no hinderance, but that by the ſupper, when we do celebrate it, this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance is renued, and more &amp; more confirmed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>What needeth it, that we haue ſo manie aſſurances of pledges &amp; tokens, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the agreement that he hath made with vs? for it might be gathered hereupon, that he ſhould be a deceiuer or inconſtant, &amp; that we
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6460:43"/>
therefore could not be to ſure and to warie in our dealing with him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>The word of God is eternall, and the effect thereof moſt ſure and certeine: euen as he being the ſpeaker, is euerlaſting and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable, his gifts and his callings without repentance, neither is our vnbeliefe able <hi>to make the Faith</hi> or truth <hi>of God of no effect. Yea</hi> (as S. Paull ſaieth) <hi>the veritie of God is more aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, through our lying, vnto his glorie.</hi> Therefore the reaſon why he ſweareth, and ſealeth his promiſes with a double ſeale, after they be made, is not, for that they are, of theire nature, doubtful &amp; vncerteine, but becauſe our hearts are ſo full of ſuſpicion and wicked diſtruſt, that we will neuer take his bare word for ſufficient aſſurance: yea, we will hardlie truſt him with all the ſolemnities of ſwearing, ſignes, and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, that are vſed of him for our warrant in this behalfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>Herein the frowardnes and wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedneſſe of our nature is the more apparant. For we can be content to reſt our ſelues wholie vpon the dreames and conceipt of our owne vaine and fooliſh wiſdome, or vpon the bare word of a mortall man, by nature a lyar, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie moment changeable: yea, diuerſe times not proouing and ſeeing vpon what ground, what reaſon and apparance it is either concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued or deliuered. Nay, we go further then ſo: for all the errors, lyes, fooleries, illuſions,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6460:43"/>
dreames, and vaine viſions that the Deuill can forge to deſtroy and ſeduce from God, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue both without anie difference or difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and alſo without anie reaſoning or deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of their nature, or of their end. I will ſaie more, that if God were on the one ſide telling vs one thing, and Satan on the other affirming the contrarie, this Father of lies and prince of darkneſſe will finde more credit and faith with vs, then God ſhall finde with all his truth and light. And hereof we haue long agone ſeene and knowne the wofull experience of our firſt parents, who being wiſer and better then all their children that came after them, onelie Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt excepted, were ſoone and eaſely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded the verie contrarie to that which God had ſpoken, yea by the ſerpent being but a beaſt, and vſing no great and long diſcourſe or manie words to confirme his ſayings. And that which maketh me to marueile, &amp; to deteſt the more our malice herein, is that we are ſo readie to receiue and beleeue whatſoeuer this wicked abuſer and deceiuer of mankinde is able to put into our eares to our deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though he haue no reaſon or argument to proue his purpoſe: &amp; that on the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary we are ſo ſlow to allow that which God doth tel vs, &amp; confirmeth by ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny oathes, ſignes, witneſſes, &amp; miracles that we might be ſaued. But I will leaue that matter to ask you another doubt, to wit, whither the vnio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whereof you haue ſpoken, which we haue with
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6460:44"/>
Ieſus Chriſt be of our bodies, or of our ſoules and minds onelie: and whither we are to go vp into heauen from the earth where we abide, or he is to come downe from heauen where he remaineth, that we may be ioyned and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled together.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>You propound a queſtion vnto me, which in theſe dayes much troubleth and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſeth the heads of manie men: yet me thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, that a man of a modeſt and ſober minde, that ſeeketh not to be contentious, might ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie himſelfe with ſo much as you haue taught vs in that point: that is to wit, that the vnion is corporall and of the bodies, but the meane is ſpirituall: euen as the vniting together of man and wife, which is the fitteſt compariſon that can in this caſe be vſed and alledged. Their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are vnited and coupled together, not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porallie, or ſo as their vnion may be diſcerned and iudged by the outward ſenſes (for we ſee that they are diuerſe times ſundred by diſtance and difference of places) but by the Faith of wedlocke which they haue mutuallie giuen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>It is not ſufficient to ſaie or to doe any thing, but the ſame muſt be with reaſon, to the edifying of them that ſee our workes, or heare our words. Wherefore <hi>Euſebius,</hi> you ſhal rehearſe, if it pleaſe you, ſuch reaſons as you take to be the fitteſt for the proouing of that which you haue ſaid.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.</note>The firſt is, that S. Paul, after he had
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6460:44"/>
taught that we are members of his bodie, of his fleſh and of his bones, alledgeth not onelie the reſemblance, but alſo the firſt inſtitution of marriage, ſaying: <hi>For this cauſe ſhall a man leaue his father and mother, and ſhall cleaue to his wife, and they twaine ſhalbe one fleſh. This is a great ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, but I ſpeake concerning Christ, and concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Church:</hi> To the ende he might ſhewe vs the meane wherby this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iunction is made; and for our better and more readie conceiuing of the ſame, that we might ſet before our eyes the vnion and coniunction that is betweene the huſband and the wife.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is, that the kingdome of Ieſus Chriſt is ſpiritual: whereupon it followeth that the order, the gouernement, the lawes, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, the power, the glorie, &amp; all other things that apperteine to the honor and renowne of a kingdome, are in the kingdome of Ieſus Chriſt ſpirituall. Therefore when we do ſpeake of the coniunction of the members with the head, which is one of the principall members, we maie not thinke, that the meane to atteine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, is other then heauenly and ſpirituall.</p>
               <p>The third is, that Ieſus Chriſt entreating of this matter couertlie vnder the figure and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of eating of his fleſh; &amp; ſeeing that ſome of his diſciples had forſaken his company, and were offended at his talke, becauſe they had not well vnderſtoode them, and had interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them carnallie: ſaid for the better &amp; more
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6460:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ample expounding of them, as followeth: <hi>It is the Spirit that quickeneth: the fleſh profiteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, the words that I ſpeake vnto you are ſpirit &amp; life.</hi> Can there be anie thing more cleare to ſhew that the eating of his fleſh, that is to ſaie, that the vnion which we haue with his huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, is made and brought to paſſe ſpirituallie? Euen as therfore the ignorance and bluntneſſe of Nicodemus deſerued to be blamed, and to be controuled of Ieſus Chriſt, becauſe he did carnally expound and conſtrue the reaſoning of Ieſus Chriſt, touching the new birth of the faithfull: ſo if anie man hearing ſpeach of the eating of his fleſh, or of the drinking of his blood, made ſimplie and according to the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, vnderſtand the ſame without all figuratiue ſpeach and ſpirituall meaning; his ignorance were not onelie to be derided as a vaine and fooliſh thing, but alſo to bee contemned as impious and tending to the diminiſhing of our faith and of the glorie of God.</p>
               <p>The fourth is, that <hi>Our Fathers</hi> (as Sainct Paul ſaith) <hi>did all eate of the ſame ſpirituall meate, and did all drinke of the ſame ſpirituall drinke: for they drank of the ſpirituall Rocke that followed them, &amp; that Rocke was Chriſt.</hi> Now certeine it is, that they could not eate that rock corporallie, as we do eat our bread made of corne: becauſe Chriſt Ieſus was not yet incarnate and made fleſh. wherefore it muſt needs follow, that as their eating is ſpiritual, ſo is our eating ſpiritual, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6460:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
wholie like vnto theirs, if we will beleeue the Apoſtle.</p>
               <p>The fift is,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>That the heauen</hi> (as Sainct Peter ſaith) <hi>muſt conteine Ieſus Chriſt, vntill the time that all things be reſtored, which God had ſpoken by the mouthe of all his Prophets ſince the world began.</hi> And this is one of the articles that we proteſt, that we hold, when we rehearſe the Creede. Therefore it is a great follie, yea an impietie, to thinke that it is requiſite for the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of his fleſh, and the drinking of his blood, that he ſhould come downe from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; that corporallie, and in perſon, he ſhoud deliuer the ſame vnto vs to that end and purpoſe.</p>
               <p>The ſixt is, that Ieſus Chriſt ſpeaking to his diſciples, ſaid vnto them,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.</note> 
                  <hi>That it was expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for them, that he ſhould leaue the world, and go his waie.</hi> Whereupon it followeth, that it ſhould be a thing not onelie vnprofitable, but alſo hurtfull and dangerous to the Church, that he ſhould returne hither in his owne bodilie ſhape before the time prefixed and purpoſed.</p>
               <p>The ſeuenth is, that the ſupper muſt be cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated in the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of him, as it is plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſhewed in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement that he gaue when he did inſtitute the ſame: nowe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance that we haue of anie matter, pre-ſuppoſeth the ſame to be abſent corporally: for otherwiſe if it be preſent, there is no more a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, but a ſight and enioying: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon it followeth, that becauſe the Supper is
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6460:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ordained to exerciſe vs in the remembrance of Ieſus Chriſt, he is abſent from vs in bodie.</p>
               <p>The eight is, that we are not commaunded to celebrate and to declare his death, but vntill the time of his comming: and therfore if he ſhould come among vs in bodie when we are aſſembled for that purpoſe, we ought to ceaſe and to leaue of this whole ceremonie.</p>
               <p>The ninth is, that as a glorious and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all bodie doth not eate: ſo it cannot be eaten corporally: for otherwiſe we might ſaie that it might bee diſgeſted in the ſtomake as other meates may be, and conſequentlie might be ſubiect to corruption: which is a thing contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the condition of bodies glorified, which are not onelie immortall, but alſo free from all corruption.</p>
               <p>The tenth is, that the thing that is not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for the life of our bodies, is not to be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten corporallie. But the fleſh of Ieſus Chriſt crucified, and his bloud ſhed for our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are not ordained for the life of the bodie, which maie be and is preſerued and kept by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes: therefore we muſt needes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that we neither eate the one, nor drinke the other corporallie.</p>
               <p>The eleuenth is, that Sainct Paul ſaith, that <hi>Meates are ordained for the bellie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>and the bellie for meates: but God ſhall deſtroy both it and them.</hi> Teaching vs, that as this life is fraile and ſubiect to corruption, ſo are alſo all thoſe bodily meats
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6460:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that are ordeined for the nouriſhment of the ſame: ſo then, if the fleſh of Chriſt were bodilie eaten, it ſhould follow that it ſhould be ſubiect to corruption: a thing cleerely &amp; meerely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to that whole diſcourſe of S. Iohn vpon this matter: <hi>whoſoeuer eateth my fleſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>hath eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life.</hi> Where he further maketh a difference betweene it &amp; Manna, giuen to our Fathers in the wilderneſſe; ſaying, that the one is corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, the other is voide and free from all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</p>
               <p>The twelfth is, that if Ieſus Chriſt were bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilie eaten, there were no neceſſitie to prooue &amp; to examin our Faith or our conſcience, when we would prepare our ſelues to the eating of his ſupper; but onelie our teeth, to wit, whither they were ſharpe, and able enough to chew it: and the ſtomach, to ſee whither it were apt to digeſt it: as we do in all other corporall meats.</p>
               <p>The thirteenth is, that we eate the fleſh, and drinke the blood of Ieſus Chriſt, euen in the ſelfe &amp; ſame maner, as the Apoſtles haue done long before vs. But they did not eate the ſame corporallie: for ſo men might haue ſeene the Apoſtles eating his bodie with their bodilie eies, euen as wel, as they did ſee his body before them, when he miniſtred the ſame vnto them. Now we muſt inferre, that no more do we eate his fleſh corporallie. If anie will ſaie, that God by a miracle prouideth that this eating be not diſcerned with bodilie eies, to the end it ſhould
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6460:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>
not be abhorred; I anſweare, that in this caſe the onelie conceipte and inward imagination were ſufficient: as we reade of S. Peter, who in a viſion abhorred the eating of thoſe creatures,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 10.</note> that were in the law forbidden to be eaten.</p>
               <p>The fourteenth is, that it is plainelie forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in Geneſis,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>To eate fleſh with the life thereof, that is, with the blood thereof.</hi> Whereupon it may be inferred, that Ieſus Chriſt, who is not come to aboliſh the law, but to fulfill the law, hath not enioyned vs a thing ſo ſtrictlie forbidden, &amp; euen more abhominable then murther. And the reaſon alleaged by S. Auguſtine, to ſhew, that al the places, wherin Ieſus Chriſt doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort his diſciples to eate his fleſh, and to drinke his blood, are vſed by waie of figured and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed ſpeaches. I wil turne the place of S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine in his booke of Chriſtian doctrine, to the end that the readers maie vnderſtand his iudgement in this matter. <hi>If there be anie ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, or anie manner of ſpeach in the Scripture</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that ſeemeth to commaund anie outrage or wickedneſſe, or contrarily, to forbid any bountifull and liberall action, the ſame is ſpoken by waie of a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure. But this ſentence following,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Except you eate the fleſh of the ſonne of man, and drinke his blood, ye haue no life in you; ſeemeth to commaund an horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and deteſtable caſe: wherefore it followeth, that this is a figure, by the which he commaundeth vs to be partakers, and to haue communion in the death and paſſion of the Lord: and for the profit and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6460:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of our conſciences, to encloſe this point within the moſt ſecret corners of our memorie, that his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie was crucified and wounded for our cauſe.</hi> This is S. Auguſtine his iudgement, which I haue turned word for word.</p>
               <p>The fifteenth is, that we cannot receiue the corporal eating of the fleſh of Ieſus Chriſt, but we muſt admit &amp; alow his bodie to be infinite: which thing entirely derogateth from the truth of his nature, and by the ſame meanes vtterly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthroweth the chiefeſt grounds &amp; moſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall foundations of our Faith. For except we beleeue him to haue bin man, and the ſonne of man in al things (our ſinnes and imperfections onely reſerued) like vnto vs: whereupon ſhall we build our aſſurance and perſuaſion, that he hath redeemed and ranſomed our nature, and that he is our high prieſt, which hath compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vpon all our infirmities? Further it maie be alleadged, that we cannot deuiſe to ſpeake any thing more fauourable and auaileable for the heriſes of Marcion and Apollinaris: the one of whom maintained that the body of Ieſus Chriſt was a fantaſtique bodie, and the other ſaid, that it was an heauenlie bodie, as the foreſaid cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall eating of the fleſh of Ieſus Chriſt is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie.</p>
               <p>The ſixteenth is, that if we eate the fleſh of Ieſus Chriſt bodilie, the ſubſtance of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies muſt of neceſſitie be augmented therebie, and nouriſhed, euen as it is by other corporall
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6460:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
meates that we receaue: a thing wholie and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together contrarie to experience, for the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the faithfull, notwithſtanding the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting onely of his fleſh, &amp; drinking of his blood, muſt of neceſſitie periſh and wither awaie, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they be nouriſhed and preſerued by ſome other food or elſe by ſome other meane.</p>
               <p>The ſeuenteenth is, that as we doe not eate corporall meates ſpirituallie: euen ſo we can not eate according to this proportion, things ſpirituall carnallie.</p>
               <p>The eighteenth is, That if we eate the fleſh of Ieſus Chriſt corporallie, ſo little a bodie as his was, being ſo broken in peices and parted, ſhould not ſuffice ſo manie, as by eating were made partakers thereof.</p>
               <p>Wherefore we may ſafely inferre vpon all theſe reaſons, that the meane whereby we are ioyned to Ieſus Chriſt is ſpirituall, and that by Faith wrought in vs by the power of the Spirite we do eate his fleſh and drinke his blood, that is to ſay, that we are vnited and ingrafted in his bodie, and more and more lincked and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied vnto him. And ſo ſaith Sainct Auguſtine verie plainelie, writing vpon the 26. Pſalme: <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith that holie father) <hi>our pledge and our aſſurance: that we by Faith, Hope, and Charitie are for euer ioyned to our head in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: as he by diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, bountie, &amp; vnion is with vs vpon the earth euen vnto the worlds end.</hi> And vpon the 30. Pſa. <hi>Whole Chriſt is the head with the bodie, the heade is the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6460:48"/>
ſauiour of the bodie, the head</hi> (I ſay) <hi>which is already aſcended vp into heauen: and the body is the church, which yet doth labour and is ſore troubled heere vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth.</hi> Now if the bodie had not bin ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and bounde to the head with a chaine of Charitie, that of the head &amp; bodie there might be made but one, he would neuer haue ſpoken from heauen in this manner rebuking that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutour Saul: <hi>Saul, Saul why perſecuteſt thou me?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 22.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>Then this ioyning is not after the manner of things natural, or conteined and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunſcribed and encloſed in any place, as the ioyning together of two ſtones in one place with lime and ſand, or of two peeces of wood the one to the other with glew; but it is a diuine and myſticall ioyning as you haue ſufficientlie declared, and what maner of faith we ought to bring with vs when we come to celebrate the Supper. Now if it pleaſe you I would haue you to proceede, &amp; to ſhew me in like manner what manner of Charitie is required.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>We maie carrie no hatred ne anie euill affection in our heart againſt our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, but forget and pardon one another all ſuch iniuries and offences as being remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred might breake or otherwiſe offende that mutuall friendſhip which ought to compaſſe in and encloſe the whole bodie of the Church. And yet thus much is not ſufficient: but we muſt moreouer, reknowledge our ſelues to bee brethren and the ſonnes of one father, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6460:49"/>
members not only of one bodie but alſo of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, haue but one heart, one ſoule and one minde. And as we haue but one Baptiſme, one Faith, one Law, one ſpirit, one ſauiour, one heritage, one hope, and one table: ſo we maie not be but one bodie in our God being euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more preſt and readie to helpe one another both with ſuch bleſſings as God hath out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlie beſtowed vpon vs, and alſo with coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, with carefulneſſe, with painfulneſſe, with our friends, and generallie with our whole ſtrength and power, whereof our neighbors may ſtand in neede. And foraſmuch as we are all of vs vnperfect in this charitie, as well as we are in Faith: when we come to the ſupper, we muſt remember to cal vpon God that it would pleaſe him to increaſe the ſame in vs by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and to forgiue vs our manifold infirmities and imperfections.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>Then it is not ſufficient that we haue this Faith and this Charitie, which you haue handled, to come to the ſupper: but it is further required that we humble our ſelues before God, and pray vnto him, that notwithſtanding our vnworthines it would pleaſe him to receiue &amp; to admit vs thereunto of his bountifull, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and free fauor.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>It is euen ſo, ſyr, as you ſaie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>May it pleaſe you, <hi>Euſebius,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe the forme both of your praier and of the confeſſion that you vſe when you come to the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6460:49"/>
Supper? might it not be ouermuch trouble vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, I would gladlie heare it in thoſe ſelfe &amp; ſame termes, wherein it is your wont and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to vtter it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>I ioyne them both together, and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling downe before God, I ſaie vnto him in this manner following.</p>
               <p>O Lord, who and what am I, that I ſhould receiue ſo manie graces &amp; fauors at thy hands? to be inuited, receiued and intreated ſo hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rablie in thy houſe? to ſit at thy table and there to be fedde and refreſhed with the fleſh and blood of thy ſonne, to be lincked and ioyned with him in ſuch ſort as we ſhall neuer be ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, to be called to take part of all the benifits and bleſſings, and to be adopted by thee into a certeine hope to be thine heire, and to enioy the glory of reſting and abiding for euer in that life and true bleſſedneſſe which thou haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and keepeſt to the benefit and behoofe of thy children? Was it not ſufficient, my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſſe and vnkindneſſe towards thee conſidered, and the ſpoile and waſt of all thy good bleſſings beſtowed vpon me remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, that when I came home againe to thee, thou wouldeſt forgiue my treſpaſſes and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and taking pitie of me thy poore creature loſt and vtterlie caſt away, thou wouldeſt make me as one of thy hired ſeruants?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 15.</note> &amp; yet <hi>Thou didſt embrace me in thine armes, and kiſſe me, and yet thou diddeſt cauſe the beſt robe to be brought forth and to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6460:50"/>
be put vppon me, thou diddeſt put a ring vppon my hand, thou diddeſt kill the fatte calfe that I might eate and be merie in ſo great ioy, and ſo good compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of my friends.</hi> Was it not ſufficient, this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing regarded that my condition was no better, and it may be, wel worſe then the condition of a dogge, that thou wouldeſt ſuffer me, <hi>onelie to gather the croomes that fell from thy table,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.</note> as the poore Cannanite beſought thee? but thou gaueſt me the whole loafe, which belongeth onelie to thy children, or that thou wouldeſt onely ſpeak the word? &amp; yet thou diddeſt come vnder my roofe, &amp; euen into my houſe to heale me. Am I more worthy, is my faith greater then the faith of the Centurio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who accounted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf vnworthy of ſo great fauor? was it not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, that as thou didſt paſſe by, thou wouldeſt vouchſafe onelie to ſpeake vnto me, &amp; to looke towards me? &amp; yet <hi>thou didſt come home with me euen into my houſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 19.</note> and thou didſt feaſt me at thy proper coſts &amp; charges, was it not ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that thou wouldſt cal me after the mariage to break my faſt with the leauings at thy table? and yet thou didſt bid me to the feaſt, &amp; receiue me to the cheifeſt of the banquet, wherein thine oxen &amp; thy fatlings were prepared &amp; ſerued. Is it not meruailous much,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.</note> that in things which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede only of thy gracious liberality, thou haſt added an oath &amp; ſignes &amp; ſeales, yea &amp; haſt left thy holy ſpirite for a gage &amp; pledge of thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, to the end we ſhold in no caſe doubt but
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6460:50"/>
that it will pleaſe thee to performe them, &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thy bond vnder ſo many aſſurances, that we might go with boldnes &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence to thy throne of thy mercy, to be helped of thee in due time, &amp; there to obtaine both pardon and life? Is it not wonderfull, that with al thy creatures thou wouldſt giue thy ſelfe vnto vs, &amp; after we haue iuſtlie deſerued manie afflictions and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, we haue contrarily receiued of thee ſo great bleſſinges as we are not able to value nor to number them, not to comprehend them, nor ſufficiently to conſider them? And what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth this, O Lord, that to make ſatiſfaction for our ſinnes &amp; to redeeme a company of robbers, murtherers, theeues, adulterers, blaſphemers, proud, couetous, traitours, faithles, liers, idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kles, &amp; ſuch roges, &amp; beggars, as weare, thou thy ſelfe haſt deliuered thy only ſon to the death, not only in hoſtage for our deliuerance, but alſo in pledge that he might abide in the ſame in our place, if happely he had not bin of ſufficient righteouſnes to ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſome vs, &amp; of ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient power to fight with death, &amp; of ſufficient life to ſwallow him vp &amp; to confound ſo dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie an aduerſarie. What meaneth this, O Lord, that thou haſt contrarie to thy iuſtice, thy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, thy cuſtome, &amp; thy promiſes not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged him for a ſeaſon, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding he was thy ſon? refuſed &amp; caſt him off, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding he entreated thee? forſaken and let him paſſe, notwithſtanding that in thee he had repoſed al
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6460:51"/>
his hope: looked vpon him without all pitie &amp; compaſſion, notwithſtanding that he endured great extremities, and that his ſoule as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe witneſſed was heauie and ſorrowfull euen vnto the death. And further, what is this, that as if thou haddeſt beene the moſt cruel tyrant that euer was heard of, thou haſt condemned him being innocent and guiltles: and curſſed him being the bleſſed ſeed, and hauing perfectly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed the whole Law: and laſtlie deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him into the hands of many executioners to be put to death betweene two theeues, the moſt ſhamefull death that euer man died: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he was righteous, faithfull, &amp; the author of life vnto all creatures. Who could be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, if thou hadſt not ſpoken it, if it were not written in thy word, if thy ſignes and tokens did not ſhew it, and laſtlie if thy holie ſpirit did not aſſure it vnto our conſciences, that a God, merciful, patient, and ſlow to anger, that a God of all comfort and conſolation, and a louing Father, as thou art, the ſtaie and refuge of all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted and forlorne perſons, the hauen and ſunnie ſeate of all thoſe that are toſſed and wearied, the freedome and ſafetie of all ſinners when they are chaſed and purſued: who would beleeue (I ſaie) that ſuch a God had locked vp as it were, al his pitie and compaſſion from his owne ſonne, and that he had now no more ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eies to behold and to looke vpon him in his diſtreſſed eſtate, nor eares to hearken vnto
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6460:51"/>
his praiers and complaints. Was it not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, that he ſhould come into the world, but he muſt liue heere in ſo great miſerie as he did? or if he muſt needs liue here; that he might not haue died? or if he muſt needs die; that he might not haue died on the croſſe? or if vpon the croſſe; it might haue beene without ſhame? or if with ſhame; it might haue beene without the curſſe? or if with curſing, at the leaſt it might not haue beene without ſome pitie on thy part? If thou be forced, after we haue infinitelie and groſſelie ſinned, to take vp thy rods and ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to giue vs due correction, thou art grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: if thou ſee that we are ſtiffnecked, thou art well contented for the firſt to let vs ſee thy rods in redineſſe: if we be not the better after that ſight, thou lifteſt thy arme, thou ſhakeſt it long before thou ſtrikeſt, thou ſtretcheſt it out, and then ſoddenlie pulleſt it in againe and withholdeſt thy ſtroke: and thou ſheweſt plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by thy countenance what griefe and paine it is vnto thee to ſmite vs: if thou ſmite vs, thou doeſt it ſparingly, and often feeleſt the hurte that thou doeſt vs ſooner then we our ſelues: if we crie out vnto thee, by and by thou cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt thy correction and repenteſt: yea we can no ſooner open our mouth to ſhew our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and to confeſſe our ſinnes vnto thee, but thou openeſt thine alſo at the ſame inſtant to forgiue the ſame, and to comfort vs in our diſtreſſe. Wherefore then being ſo gentle and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6460:52"/>
eaſie towards vs who are no other then wolfes and verie Deuils in the ſhape of men haſt thou helde ſo hard and ſo ſharpe an hand o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer this Lambe, who is ſo much more migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, vnſpotted, and innocent then all his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, as they cannot haue the like prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence and aduantage ouer vs? what had he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued to be ſo little ſpared? or we, to be ſo greatlie forborne? if he haue not offended, in <hi>That he made himſelfe of no value and tooke on him the forme of a ſeruant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>when as he, being in the forme of God, thought it no robberie to be equall with God his Father, and in that he humbled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and became obedient vnto the death, euen the death of the croſſe.</hi> Wherein hath he ſo great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie offended, that he ſhould deſerue ſo ſtrange and rigorous puniſhment? If Satan himſelfe, as Sainct Matthew ſaide, could place his hope in thee, and call vpon thee, he ſhould finde place alſo in thy grace and mercie: and yet thy ſonne who felt in his ſoule an horrible diſtreſſe, and was oppreſſed with the anguiſhes and panges of death, notwithſtanding his often cryings &amp; humble requeſts and praiers, yea the bloodie ſweate that dropped downe his face, euen vnto the earth for verie anguiſh &amp; paine that he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured in bearing that huge and heauie burthen which thou didſt laie vpon his ſhoulders, could not in the extremitie of this his miſerie prouoke one drop of pitie &amp; compaſſion in thy bowels. What meaneth all this I ſaie? alas! O Lord, I
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6460:52"/>
may not enquire, nor reaſon long with thee to ſeeke the cauſe thereof and to vnderſtande it. For it is nothing elſe but a ſingular and ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne mercie which it pleaſed thee to ſhew vs that we might be ſaued: and on the other ſide, the like iuſtice which thou haſt executed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy ſonne, in him to puniſh our treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and tranſgreſſions. It is we that haue ſinned, and it was thy pleaſure that he ſhould receiue the ſhame, the condemnation and the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: he was righteous, and the onelie innocent and guiltleſſe before thee in all the world, yet his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie did profite him nothing to eſcape thy iudgement. For we haue gathered the fruite, &amp; by thy grace haue receaued the glorie, the life, the reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence, &amp; generally al the good things that he had deſerued: he was made a ſinner in vs, &amp; we are made righteous in him: he became poore, to make vs rich: ſicke, to make vs whole: low &amp; humble, that we might be exalted &amp; ſet aloft: and receaued nothing of vs but a mortall miſerie, giuing vs in counterexchange a bleſſed life, ſo certein, as it cannot be changed, ſo great, as it cannot be encreaſed, ſo laſting, as it can neuer be ended. Before, by our ſinnes &amp; euil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, we were loſt, but now, by thy gracious fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and by the merites of thy Sonne we are found againe: before, we were deade, but now we are raiſed vp againe: we were baniſhed out of thy preſence and out of thy realme, but now we are called backe againe, &amp; our baniſhment
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6460:53"/>
is repealed: we were the ſeruants and ſlaues of Satan, in continual feare of death: but now we are made thy friends and children, to whom by promiſe thou haſt giuen a certeine hope of life. Out of hel in a mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thou haſt raiſed &amp; lifted vs vp into heauen, &amp; of earth and doung (as we were) thou haſt made vs pretious veſſels vnto thy golrie. The very depth of darknes remained in vs and in our nature: but by the power of thy word &amp; of thy Spirit, thou haſt cauſed the day to ſhine continuallie in thy church, and that ſome of the members of the ſame do glyſter as the ſtarres of heauen, other more bright then the Sunne it ſelfe. This is our ſecond creation, thus haſt thou of nothing renued vs the ſecond time, and made vs of nothing new creatures. S. Peter perceiuing that he was eſcaped out of the hands of Herod, and out of the priſon, wherein he was ſo ſtreightlie kept and locked, thought for a ſeaſon that he dreamed of his deliuerance. And is not this a dreame, O Lord? or is it true? I meane that which I thinke and ſpeake of thy innumerable graces toward vs, &amp; of this moſt bleſſed freedome, wherein thou haſt ſet vs by the death of thy Sonne. No, no, it is no dreame by any meanes. For there is nothing ſo certeine as thy graces &amp; bleſſings vpon al thoſe, that wil receiue them with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence in thy promiſes. I cannot ſpeake in the honor of them ſo much as I conceiue, nor conceiue ſo much as I beleeue, nor beleeue ſo much as is in truth. For they are
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:6460:53"/>
ſo great, that my tongue, my cogitations, and my Faith cannot reach &amp; atteine, nor meaſure the greatneſſe and height thereof. Dauid conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the infinite vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiuable malice &amp; wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe of mankind, aſked this queſtion, <hi>whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there were any that could reckon and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand their faultes?</hi> But contrarilie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.12.</note> I aſke this queſtion: who is he that can number, or ſpeake, or thinke of al thy benefits? For albeit that our ſin aboundeth, yet thy grace aboundeth more: without the which, O Lord, what ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of me? whither ſhould I go? what hope ſhould remaine for me? vpon the earth there is nothing but thy curſſe: from heauen thy wrath is reueiled vpon my wickednes and vnbeliefe: in al things that are vnder the ſun, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but vanitie. Therefore when I looke to ſee from whence my helpe ſhall come, after I haue caſt mine eies euery way round about me, I muſt of force confeſſe with thy Prophet, that <hi>from thy goodneſſe onely I am to looke and to wayte for my help:</hi> and,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 52.</note> 
                  <hi>that among men there is giuen no other name vnder heauen, whereby we muſt be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, then the name of thy ſonne.</hi> I am wicked and wretched more then I can expreſſe: but thou art good and mercifull, more then I can thinke or conceiue, when I looke vpon my ſelfe, al my hope of ſaluation departeth: but as ſoone as thou turneſt thy face towards me, by &amp; by my hope returneth, namelie, when thou ſheweſt in thy countenance the compaſſion that thou
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6460:54"/>
takeſt of my miſerie, to defend me againſt the fanſies and illuſions of my carnal vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and to vphold me in the dreadfull and terrible ſkirmiſhes, wherewith my poore and weake conſcience is often aſſailed &amp; ſore ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to repel and to driue backe al the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the wicked Spirit, &amp; to giue me courage and an aſſured hardineſſe againſt thoſe horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble threatnings layd out in thy law agaynſt all the tranſgreſſors of the ſame: and in briefe, to keepe me from falling, and to lift me vp when I am downe, I haue no other meane but thy mercie, and the grace that thou haſt promiſed me by the merits of thy ſonne. This is my forte &amp; caſtle, when I am beſeiged by the enimie of my ſaluation, &amp; my place of refuge and reſcue, when thy wrath and iudgements do follow &amp; purſue me. This is the ſtaffe and the proppe, not onelie of my age, but alſo of my whole life: for there is no parte or age of my life, wherein I am not ſo weake, that without it I cannot be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſtand. O moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; perfect receipt, which neuer man yet prooued, but was cured of his ſickneſſe, and redilie found remedy of al his diſeaſes. Am not I greatlie bound to the, that thou haſt taught me this receipte? and further, that thou haſt made it for my vſe, &amp; applied it to my infirmitie, and healed me by it? O good God! O how great and how wonderfull is thy goodneſſe? There is nothing ſo great, as I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as are the benefits that thou haſt beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:6460:54"/>
vpon me, &amp; doeſt continue vpon me day by day. And yet I muſt beleeue and confeſſe, that they are ſmall, &amp; almoſt of no price, in reſpect of thoſe, which thou keepeſt in ſtore for me, &amp; I looke for and hope for at thy hands. But this ſeemeth a verie pitiful caſe, that they ſhould be ſo great; and on the contrarie, that my Faith ſhould be ſo litle and ſo weake to receiue them, and my ſpirit ſo rude &amp; ignorant to vnderſtand them, and my tongue ſo vnſmooth to expreſſe them, and that which is worſt of al, my affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo cold to acknowledge &amp; to eſteeme them at their price and value. And yet this curſed and damnable vnthankfulneſſe of mine doth not withdraw thy goodneſſe &amp; largeneſſe towards me, which day by day thou doſt continue more and more, yea in ſuch ſort, as the latter fauour and graces which thou ſheweſt me, do far ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount &amp; ſurpaſſe the former, which thou haſt beſtowed vpon me. It is not poſſible to reckon or to imagine the thankes that I owe vnto the: the let &amp; the hinderance whereof is partlie my owne inſufficiencie and weakeneſſe, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie the hugeneſſe and infinite number of thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifits. But to diſcouer all my ſhame and all my nakedneſſe vnto the, it proceedeth from the ſmall remembrance and feeling that I haue of thy goodneſſe, what remaineth, but that I ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be eſteemed altogether vnthankfull towards thee? nothing remaineth, but onlie to pray thee that thou wouldſt open my lippes by thy holie
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:6460:55"/>
Spirit, to the end that I may acknowledge and confeſſe mine vnthankefulneſſe and vnworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to be ſorowfull that I can no better feele and conceiue of thy benifits in my heart, to cry out alowd, that thou art infinite in goodneſſe, who haſt beſtowed ſo manie graces vpon me, and that for my part I am infinite in wickednes, who do price, eſteeme, &amp; regard them ſo litle: and in generall to proteſt in publique, that my ſaluation proceedeth from thee, &amp; my deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from my ſelfe, if it were not thy good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of thy ſingular grace &amp; fauor to prouide for &amp; to meete with that inconuenience. Helpe me now, ô Lord, that I may do this by the whole courſe of my life, and that the readines &amp; good affection hereunto, that thou haſt giuen me at this preſent, be not in vayne &amp; of none effect. Suffer me not, ô God my father, to take delight &amp; pleaſure in any other thing, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, meditation, ſpeaking, &amp; praiſing of thy mercy and great fauors towards me: &amp; of the contrarie, to take no greater ſorrow &amp; diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, then in the crimes, offences, and lewde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanours, that I commit againſt thy Maieſtie. This is the praier and confeſſion that I make, before I come to the table of my Sauiour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>Yet this is not all that I will require: for you muſt now let me vnderſtand, what you thinke at the verie inſtant, when the bread and wine is miniſtred?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Euſeb.</speaker>
               <p>The bread and wine that I take, that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:6460:55"/>
I ſee and behold, and that I taſte, are, as it were, certeine ſteps and traces, to guid, and to lift vp my ſpirit by litle and litle, to the regard and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of that league and alliance, which God hath made with vs, of the forgiueneſſe of my ſinnes, of life euerlaſting, of the adoption of children, of the inheritance of the kingdome of heauen, of al ſpiritual ioye, of perpetual reſt, of glorie, of grace, of peace, and in generall, of all the great and true felicities therein contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. After that I cal to minde Ieſus Chriſt, the Mediatour and worker of this new league, who hath by his death found means, that it ſhalbe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileable, and of full ſtrength and vertue, and cancelling the bond &amp; obligation wherein we were bound before, and acquitted vs, and ſet vs free from al the whole curſſe. Thence I go far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and I come on to behold the charitie and loue of God towards vs, not able to be concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; who ſpared not his onely Sonne, but deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered him and gaue him ouer to the death, that he might make ſatiſfaction for our iniquities and offences. Laſtly, I doe ſhut vp my inward thoughts, with repeating ouer and ouer, when I ariſe from the table, how manie waies I am bound vnto him, and with rendring vnto him ſuch thankes, as it pleaſeth him to inſpire into my heart.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miniſt.</speaker>
               <p>You haue greatlie ſatiſfied &amp; conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me, <hi>Euſebius,</hi> in al your anſwers: &amp; I thanke God for the knowledge, that he hath giuen
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6460:56"/>
you of the ſubſtance &amp; meaning of this miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: beſeeching him, (to the end it be not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned &amp; made vnholie) that by his good will and pleaſure al ſuch, as ſhalbe to celebrate the ſame myſterie, may haue like meaſure of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. And now, becauſe I haue no lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to continue longer with you, I wil commit you to God, and leaue you to his protection, vntill our next meeting.</p>
            </sp>
            <div type="treatise">
               <head>A TREATISE OF THE TRVE SACRIFICE AND TRVE PRIEST. <hi>Made by I. de l'Espine, Minister of the word of God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere be many that meruaile why we refuſe and condemne the Maſſe with ſo great conſtancie and vehemencie, and ſlaunder vs grieuouſly in that reſpect: ſpredding &amp; ſowing rumors of vs in the eares of the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and alſo of great and mightie Princes, that we are opinatiue, arrogant, ſeditious, rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, factious, and manie other ſlaunderous lyes wherewith they do fill and breake continuallie the eares of the vnlearned and ignorant, and of thoſe that take any delight in hearing them. But to ſhew that we are not ledde by any opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion or fond and fooliſh fancie, nor by ſeeking of any vaine glorie, nor by any other paſſion
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:6460:56"/>
which troubleth and carieth away our wits, I wil in this ſmal treatiſe render reaſon, as it were in a ſumme, of that which we hold and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine, to euery one that is willing to know the ſame. And I doubt not, my Lord, if it wil pleaſe you to do me ſo much fauour as to reade and to marke my writing, but you will ſtoppe your eares henceforth againſt the lying and ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſpeaches of our aduerſaries whereby they ſeeke to defame &amp; to diſcredite vs, and in time you will take vpon you the protection and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of our cauſe.</p>
               <p>I will not ſpende time in expounding the name of the Maſſe, nor in ſhewing of what pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in what age, and by whom it was firſt pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched together: neither will I blaſe the croſſes and other pettie aperies and monkeries therein vſed, ſeruing more to moue laughter then to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difie in true pietie &amp; godlineſſe. All ſuch trifles I will ouerpaſſe, and wil handle onely the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and moſt principall points, ſuch as are thought to be the grounds and foundations of the Maſſe, namely the office of the Prieſt, the Sacrifice, and the things that haue beene added to the one and the other.</p>
               <p>Touching the office of the Preiſt it is an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and an eſtate, the title &amp; execution where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of cannot belong to any other then to Ieſus Chriſt. For we beleeue, that he alone is our Chriſt, that is to ſaie; he whom God the Father hath anoynted and ordeined to be our king:
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:6460:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that hee might gouerne and defende vs: and our Prophet to teach and to inſtruct vs in all things apperteining to our ſaluation, and to his honor and glorie: and our Prieſt to offer Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and by his ſacrifice to appeaſe the heauie wrath and diſpleaſure of God againſt vs: and further to praie and to make interceſſion for vs, and by his ſute to entertaine and to keepe vs in his fauour. Therefore euen as it were blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, to acknowledge &amp; approoue any other king and lawmaker to rule and to gouerne our conſciences then Ieſus Chriſt, or any other ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter &amp; teacher then him to traine vs vp in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of God: ſo we commit blaſphemie againſt his honor, if we admit or acknowledge anie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prieſt to ſacrifice for vs then him.</p>
               <p>Further, no man may attribute vnto himſelfe any honor herein <hi>Except he be called thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to of God, as Aaron was.</hi> But there is none ſaue onelie Ieſus Chriſt, whom God hath glorified by ordeining and creating him high Prieſt, and to whom he hath ſaid, <hi>Thou art my Sonne, this day haue I begotten thee.</hi> Whereupon it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that vnto him alone belongeth this honor and dignitie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.26.</note>Againe the qualities and conditions of the Prieſt of the new Teſtament are theſe, that he be <hi>holie, innocent, vnspotted, ſeparated from ſinners, and exalted far aboue the heauens.</hi> Which points cannot belong to any other the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Ieſus Chriſt, becauſe al men, he only excepted, being borne
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:6460:57"/>
and brought foorth of fleſh, are fleſh, that is to ſaie, defiled &amp; ſinful, as their parents were, and therefore vncapeable of the Prieſthood.</p>
               <p>Againe, the Prieſt muſt be eternall and <hi>for euer, after the order of Melchiſedech:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.3.</note> that is to ſaie, as it is expounded by the Apoſtle, <hi>without father, without mother, without kindred, hauing neither beginning of his dayes, neither end of his life.</hi> Which cannot be applied to our Prieſts nor to any mortall man.</p>
               <p>Againe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.22.</note> 
                  <hi>He needeth not daylie to offer vp Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for his owne ſinnes, as the Priestes of Leui did neede.</hi> From which neceſſitie there is none that can be freed and deliuered, but onely Ieſus Chriſt; inſomuch as by reaſon of ſinne abiding in them, and of infirmities wherewith they are incloſed and compaſſed, they haue neede con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuallie to pray vnto God and to aske him par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for the ſame.</p>
               <p>Again, if any other were capeable of the eſtate of the Prieſthood then Ieſus Chriſt, they muſt needs be Prieſts after one of theſe two orders: to wit, of Leui, or of Melchiſedech: but they cannot be after the order of Leui, becauſe all the ancient ceremonies, yea, and the Law it ſelf that commanded them, are now aboliſhed. So it ſhould remaine that <hi>They must be after the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Melchiſedech.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.</note> But that is no more poſſible the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other, becauſe they ſhould be Prieſts for euer, which is not incident to any mortall man.</p>
               <p>Againe, the Prieſt muſt be more worthie &amp;
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:6460:58"/>
honorable then the ſacrifice that he doth offer: for the Sacrifice of whatſoeuer it be, cannot pleaſe God, but onely in reſpect of him that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth. And it is the reaſon alledged by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.</note> why <hi>Abel by Faith did offer vnto God a more excellent Sacrifice then Cain:</hi> meaning thereby that the price and worthineſſe of the Sacrifice proceeded hence, that he which offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red being faithfull, was by Faith acceptable to God. Whereupon it muſt needes be that if the Maſſe Prieſts were true ſacrificing Prieſts and did offer Ieſus Chriſt in their Maſſe, as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, that they ſhould be of more worthineſſe and honor then he, and that he ſhould not be in the fauor of God but by their credit and fauor.</p>
               <p>Laſtlie, whoſoeuer is Prieſt, by the ſame meane is become Mediator betweene God &amp; man, for the end of the Sacrifice is to procure the remiſſion of ſinnes, and ſo conſequently to reconcile man vnto God. So if the Maſſeprieſts could be Sacrificing Prieſts they ſhould alſo be Mediators, which they cannot be. For euen as there is but one God, ſo there is but one Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator betweene God and man. And thus yee ſee by theſe proofes that the name, the title, and dignitie of Prieſthood cannot belong to anie other then to Ieſus Chriſt, and without great and monſtrous blaſphemie that we cannot at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute the ſame to any other.</p>
               <p>In like manner it is he onely that can exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe the office of prieſthood: for the Prieſt muſt
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:6460:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>
appeaſe the wrath of God, and reconcile him vnto men that are in his diſpleaſure, And this is not poſſible to be done, without a moſt perfect obedience: euen as his wrath &amp; heauy diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure at the beginning was ſtirred vp &amp; inflamed againſt vs by no other thing, then the diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of our firſt parents. But none is able, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept Ieſus Chriſt alone, to yeld ſuch obedience to God as is required, by reaſon of the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; integritie of his nature. Therefore for this reſpect, no man can execute the office of the Preiſt but he.</p>
               <p>Further, the Prieſt muſt ſatiſfie the iuſtice of God for the iniquities and tranſgreſſions of thoſe, in whoſe fauour he offereth the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, inaſmuch as he appeereth and preſenteth himſelfe before him, as a pledge and a ſuretie for their debts: which no carnal and ſinful man is able to performe. For how ſhould he acquite the debts of another,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 7.</note> being himſelfe alwaies indebted, and vnable to pay his owne? as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peereth by the parables of thoſe two, that were bound to one creditor, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they could not pay &amp; ſatiſfie: and of him,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Marth.</hi> 18.</note> that ought the King ten talents, which by no means he was able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge: and by the ordinarie confeſſion of the Church,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.</note> which (I ſay) the Catholique Church doth make vnto God, praying for the remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and forgiueneſſe of her ſinnes and offences. Wherefore, there is no other, that can in this point diſcharge the office &amp; dutie of the Prieſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:6460:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.</note>Again, <hi>The Prieſt muſt obteine remiſſion of ſins for thoſe for whom he doth ſacrifice,</hi> which cannot be obteined without ſheading of blood:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.22.</note> 
                  <hi>For without ſheading of blood</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>is no remiſſion.</hi> And this blood may not be the blood of bulls, goates, calues, lambes, or of anie other beaſt, which cannot purge &amp; purifie the conſcience; but it muſt be the blood of the Prieſt himſelfe, &amp; the ſame without ſpot. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then that neuer in the world there hath bin blood with that conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but onely the blood of Ieſus Chriſt, we may hereby well conclude, that it is he onely, that can execute the office of the Prieſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.17.</note>Againe, the Prieſt muſt procure the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming &amp; ratifying of the Teſtament, and of the new league and alliance with God. <hi>But the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament is yet of no force, as long as he that made it is aliue.</hi> If the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our Maſſeprieſts could be true ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificing Prieſts, they ought, for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of their duetie &amp; charge, to dye, &amp; ſo to become teſtators, to the end, that by their death the Teſtament might be confirmed. Now they are no Teſtators, becauſe they are not God; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do they yet die: and albeit they ſhould die yet their death would not be auailable to the confirming of the Teſtament, which they had not made before, wherefore it followeth, that they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not exerciſe the ſtate of the Prieſthood.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.26.</note>Further, <hi>The office of the Prieſt is to deſtroye ſinne:</hi> as the Apoſtle ſheweth, which is not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:6460:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>
for any mortal man to doe, being the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant and ſlaue of ſinne, bearing it about him in his boſome, nouriſhing &amp; mainteining it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually with him, giuing it being, ſtrength, &amp; vigour, bringing it forth of his mothers womb, and keeping it euer after vntill his dying day; &amp; being vnable to liue without it, ſo greatly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to deſtroy it, that if it were dead in him, he would quicken and reuiue it. Seeing then that there is none but <hi>Ieſus Christ, that is come into the world, to deſtroy ſinne, and the other workes of the Deuil</hi> (as S. Iohn ſaith) there is none but he that can execute the office of the Prieſt.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, the office of a <hi>Mediator,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.</note> 
                  <hi>is to appeare before the face of God, continuallie to make inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for vs, and to keepe vs in his grace &amp; fauor.</hi> But none, ſaue only Ieſus Chriſt, can performe this poynt. For Iſaiah the Prophet, ſpeaking of men, ſaith in this manner:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſaie</hi> 33.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Who among vs ſhall dwell with the deuouring fire? who among vs ſhall dwell with the euerlaſting burnings?</hi> And Dauid confirmeth the ſame, ſaying; <hi>The fooliſh ſhal not ſtand before thy face, nor come into thy preſence: thou hateſt all them that worke iniquitie.</hi> Then if no man be altogether pure and free from foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhnes, but euery one committeth often times iniquitie, we muſt inferre hereupon, that the Maſſeprieſts, which are like other men, haue neede them ſelues of one to preſent them vnto God, and to bring them to the preſence of his Maieſtie, which otherwiſe they were not able
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:6460:60"/>
to come vnto, ſo much are they vnable to bring in a ſinner into the preſence of God, to begge his pardon, or by their own credit and fauor to inclyne and to bend the Maieſtie of God to ſhew him fauour.</p>
               <p>We haue ſhewed, that the Prieſt muſt pacifie the wrath, &amp; appeaſe the anger of God. Now I ſaie that he is to paſſe on farther, and namely, to charge his owne ſhoulders with the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of God his wrath, to the end that he maie diſcharge thoſe, that he would reconcile vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. Now we are to conſider what ſtrength a mortal man can haue, to beare ſo great and ſo heauie a burthen, as the heauen, the earth, the mountains, and the whole frame of the world is not able to endure. Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing innocent, the arme, the power, &amp; the right hand of God, did ſhrinke, and ſweate blood in great aboundance, for the hugeneſſe and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines of this burthen, when he had taken it vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his ſhoulders. For it was the verie feeling of the iudgement of God, and not of the death of the bodie, which cauſed him to feele ſuch an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes as he endured &amp; complained of, when the houre of his crucifiing was at hand. And how then can a poore Chaplin, cloathed with al manner of iniquitie, &amp; drinking downe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe as water, be ſo hardie as to offer himſelfe to beare ſo heauie a burthen, vnder which Ieſus Chriſt, with al his ſtrength and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie, remained almoſt ouerwhelmed?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:6460:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>Laſtly, the office of the Prieſt is,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>To haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion of the infirmities of al the elect that are in the world,</hi> to comfort them, and to ſweeten the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe of their euils and ſorrowes. And this is not to be done of any, but onely of Ieſus Chriſt: becauſe there is none but he, that can vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them, and prouide remedy for them. For the men of the Weſt cannot learne the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of them that dwel in the Eaſt: nor they of the South, the miſeries of thoſe that inhabit the North, by which reaſon, they cannot take any pitie either of other, nor prouide due remedies for them, by reaſon of their weakenes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiencie. By this reaſon with the former we may conclude, that they can by no meanes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute the office and eſtate of the Prieſthood.</p>
               <p>We haue prooued, that our Prieſts cannot be true Prieſts for ſacrifice, neither yet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge that office. Now let vs prooue in like manner, that their ſacrifice cannot be auaylea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble nor forceable to pleaſe or to appeaſe God, nor any maner of way to procure or to obteine the remiſſion of ſinnes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, a ſacrifice, to be of ſuch a propertie, muſt be perfect, as Moſes taught vs in the law: when as by the ordinance of God he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſo expreſſely, that the beaſts, which ſhould be offered vnto him, to ſhadow him, ſhould be <hi>perfect, &amp; without blemiſh, &amp; whole of al their mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</hi> But the ſacrifices of men cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, becauſe they themſelues being vnperfect,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:6460:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and al their workes vnperfect, haue not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their perſonnes, or of their righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, any other perfection then that which is imputed vnto them by the grace of God, in the name and fauor of Ieſus Chriſt. Therefore it followeth, that they can offer nothing vnto God, that may make him well pleaſed and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorable vnto ſinners.</p>
               <p>Further, it is required, that all Sacrifices (as al other workes) ſhould be ioyned with obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, &amp; ſo by conſequent, that they ſhould be commanded. For otherwiſe they ſhould be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered without Faith, &amp; ſo become abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before God. Yea the verie ſacrifice, that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt did make of his owne bodie, if it had not beene foreappointed of his Father, had not beene receiued nor accepted. And therefore it is, that he maketh the greateſt reckoning and the greateſt accompte of his obedience. For thus he ſaith:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Burntoffering and ſinoffering haſt thou not required: then ſaid I: loe, I come. For in the roll of the booke it is written of me, that I ſhould do thy will, o God.</hi> S. Paul in like manner doth at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute al the fruite and profite, that commeth by the death of Ieſus Chriſt to his obedience, when he ſaith, <hi>That he became obedient to his father euen vntill the death,</hi> and therefore that God had <hi>highlie exalted him.</hi> Nowe let our preiſtes ſhew vs by ſcripture, that God hath commanded them to chaunte &amp; to ſing maſſe, if they wil haue vs to approue their ſacrifice. If
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:6460:61"/>
they cannot do it, no more can we without it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouch their ſacrifice to haue power and vertue to ſatiſfie and to pleaſe God as they doe hold, neither yet that it is acceptable nor holy before God. Againe the power of ſuch a ſacrifice muſt be eternall and infinite that it may ſurpaſſe and exceede the diſobedience of the firſt Adam. And as the one hath ſpread abroad the poyſon thereof, &amp; a general calamity vpon all the men in the world, in what countrie, time, or age ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they haue liued: ſo the obedience of the ſecond Adam being oppoſed to that of the firſt muſt bring a generall bleſſing &amp; felicitie vpon al them, that are predeſtinate to eternal life: to the end, <hi>That where ſinne hath abounded,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>there the grace of God might more abound.</hi> But the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a Popiſh Prieſt cannot haue this vertue and power, yea leſſe then the ancient ſacrifices of the Prieſts of Leui, which were ordeined &amp; appointed of God, and were a type and ſhadow of Ieſus Chriſt. Then let vs conclude againſt their opinion, that it neither is, nor can be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to pleaſe God.</p>
               <p>Alſo, the ſacrifice, wherewith God muſt be pleaſed, and his wrath appeaſed, muſt be but one: for otherwiſe it ſhould not be perfect, if it were renewed, neither the power and vertue thereof infinite, wherefore the Preiſts that ſing ſo many maſſes, doe euidently declare by the multiplying of their Sacrifices, that they are vnperfect, and therefore they cannot be propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatorie;
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:6460:62"/>
that is to ſay, of nature and force to pleaſe and to ſatiſfie God. If they ſaie (as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlie they do) that they offer Ieſus Chriſt; we anſwere: Firſt, it cannot be ſo: becauſe <hi>Ieſus Chriſt can die no more:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.</note> which muſt needes be, if he were ſacrificed againe: becauſe there is no Sacrifice without death.</p>
               <p>Secondlie, this renewing of the Sacrifice ſhould be vnprofitable and ſeruing to no vſe, in reſpect of the remiſſion of ſinnes, which by Faith we do beleeue and obteine:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.</note> for <hi>Where no remiſſion is, there is no more ſacrifice for ſinne.</hi> For if the end of the Sacrifice be, to ſanctifie and to perfect him, for whom it is offered; what need we to haue anie more ſacrifices, ſeeing that by the ſacrifice,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.</note> that Ieſus Chriſt did offer vnto God, of his owne body, we are already ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and made holie for euer.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it would be a great preiudice, and a notorious iniurie to him, if his Sacrifice ſhould be renewed and offered againe by any other, then by himſelfe. For if it were ſo, then ſhould he be robbed and ſpoiled of his honor,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.</note> and the oblation that he made once of his body, ſhould be reputed and taken as vnperfect and inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient: for the renewing is a certeine reaſon and argument of imperfection.</p>
               <p>And if there were other Prieſts to offer gifts and ſacrifices for ſinne,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.</note> and Ieſus Chriſt were yet abiding vpon the earth, he ſhould be no Preiſt at all. For if he were Preiſt, he ſhould be
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:6460:62"/>
Prieſt alone, neither can he haue any fellow to be ioined and aſſociate vnto him in the Preiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, no more then in his other offices. So we may be reſolued, that we ne haue, ne can haue other Preiſt to reconcile vs to God, then Ieſus Chriſt: ne other ſacrifice then that, which he hath once offered, to purchaſe vnto vs remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of al our ſinnes. And ſo <hi>He is both the Prieſt, and alſo the oblation,</hi> as ſaith S. Auguſtine. For as there was neuer in the world anie perfect bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, ſaue his onely, worthie to be offered vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God in ſacrifice: ſo there was neuer anie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man ſo perfect, as he was fit and capable to offer vp the ſame bodie in ſacrifice.</p>
               <p>The third point, which we haue to conſider in the Maſſe, is touching certaine things an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the ſacrifice and to the Prieſthood: which poynt maie briefelie and in fewe words be diſpatched. For they are confeſſions, prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, or praiſes, or the reading of Epiſtles and Goſpels, or of ceremonies. As concerning prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſuch as are the oriſons or confeſſions, made at the beginning &amp; entrance of the Maſſe, they are to be reiected and refuſed: becauſe they are for the moſt parte, againſt the expreſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God, conſecrated to creatures.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.</note> As concerning praiers, this is much vngodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes or impietie, and no leſſe infidelitie or vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe in them, foraſmuch as the interceſſion or merite of ſome Saincte is moſt commonlie mingled and ioyned with them.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioſue.</hi> 7.</note> As for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:6460:63"/>
of the Epiſtle and Goſpell, in that the name of God is vſed &amp; taken in vaine, becauſe they be redde in a ſtrange language, it cannot bring any edifiing to the congregation. As for the ceremonies, to the end I ſaie nothing more grieuous, they are al ſuperſtitious, becauſe they are al the inuentions of men, without any ſence or ſignification, ſaue onlie ſuch, as ſlumbering and dreaming Monckes haue forged in their mindleſſe and witleſſe braines, and after haue pleaſed to beſtowe vpon them: yea ſome of them are meere idolatries: as the worſhiping of the bread, cenſing, and kneeling.</p>
               <p>By this that hath bin diſcourſed, as in a ſumme, touching the chiefe and principall poyntes of the Maſſe, euerie one maie iudge what it is, and in what accompte &amp; reckoning to be holden, and whither we haue manie and ſufficient reaſons to condemne, and to abhorre it, and to withdrawe all men from taking parte in ſo horrible blaſphemies &amp; impieties, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it is pieced and patched together.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.</note> For, <hi>It is impoſſible</hi> (as S. Paul ſaith) <hi>that we can be partakers of the Lord his table, &amp; of the table of deuils.</hi> Then whoſoeuer he be that goeth to the Maſſe, he leaueth, in ſo doing, the Lord his table, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaketh al the benefits there preſented: that is to ſaie, he renounceth the ſacrifice of Ieſus Chriſt and al that thereupon dependeth: to witte, his righteouſnes, life, the grace of God, and all the happineſſe that he is to hope for, and to looke
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:6460:63"/>
for one daie in his kingdome.</p>
               <p>There be ſomme that ſaie (to cloake and to couer their forfeit and offence in this behalfe) that albeit they are preſent at Maſſe, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they meane not to be partakers thereof, but in trueth it is not poſſible for a man to do the one, but he ſhal committe the other. For as S. Paul ſaith,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>He that eateth of the fleſh of the ſacrifices, is he not partaker of the altar?</hi> that is to ſay, whoſoeuer commeth to the ceremonies, maketh preſent profeſſion, that he is partaker of the miſteries therein vnderſtood and taught, that he that goeth to the Maſſe, forſaketh and departeth from the table and benefites of Ieſus Chriſt. This reaſon onely might be ſufficent to withdraw all men from the ſame, and to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that they ſhould not be preſent: and alſo that we haue an expreſſe commandement, <hi>that by no meanes we do communicate with the vnfuite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full workes of darkenes, but rather that we do blame them and reprehend them.</hi> Againe, <hi>That we do not couple our ſelues with infidels: that we departe out of their companie:</hi> that we ſeperate our ſelues from ſuch, and handle nothing that is defiled or vncleane, for the reaſons following: <hi>Becauſe there is no fellowſhippe betweene righteouſneſſe and vnrighteouſneſſe, betweene light and darkeneſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Chriſt and Belial, betweene the faithfull and the infidel, laſtly, betweene the temple of God and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doles.</hi> Againe, we are commanded <hi>To depart out of Babylon, that we be not partakers of her ſinnes,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:6460:64"/>
nor feele her woundes.</hi> Which teſtimonies of Scripture are cleare &amp; plaine enoughe to turne aſide the mindes of all men, that they haue no fellowſhippe nor agreement with infidels, and chieflie in the exerciſe of religion, and of all things thereunto belonging.</p>
               <p>I beſech God who hath giuen you, my Lord, this willingnes and deſire to be informed of this great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe, I meane of the Maſſe, that it would pleaſe him to lighten your vnderſtanding that you mai rightly and truely conceaue this treatiſe, breifely handeled and in fewe wordes: and to geue you ſuch ſtrength and fit occaſions, as you may thereby be hable to withdrawe your ſelfe wholy from all theſe curſed abominations and horrible impieties, no doubte the cauſe &amp; princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall roote and ſpring of all the miſeries and curſinges that are this day throughout the whole worlde. And ſurely, my Lord, there is no other waie to win and to keepe the fauour of God, from the which onelie you are to looke for all the honour, proſperitie, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, that you deſire and promiſe to your ſelfe, then to ſeeke by al meanes poſſible the ſetting vp of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and honour: yealding and applying your ſelfe with your whole hearte to his whole pleaſure: &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarilie, eſchewing and auoyding whatſoeuer may of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and diſpleaſe him: chiefelie and principallie, all the kindes of idolatrie, which aboue all other crimes and ſinnes is moſt odious to him and moſt abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. I praie God to giue you the grace to ſeeke, and to procure vnto him this honour and ſeruice.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:6460:64"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
